<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The right receiving of Christ· Or, An appendix to the worthy communicant, or A treatise shewing the due order of receiving the sacrament. By Jer. Dyke, late minister of Epping in Essex. Which was intended by the said author in his life time to be annexed to this treatise of the sacrament; as appeares in the epistle. Wherein a Christian may know, whether he hath rightly received Christ in the sacrament or no.</title>
            <author>Dyke, Jeremiah, 1584-1639.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 160 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81950</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2959bA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229229</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896163</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896163</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153914</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81950)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153914)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2388:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The right receiving of Christ· Or, An appendix to the worthy communicant, or A treatise shewing the due order of receiving the sacrament. By Jer. Dyke, late minister of Epping in Essex. Which was intended by the said author in his life time to be annexed to this treatise of the sacrament; as appeares in the epistle. Wherein a Christian may know, whether he hath rightly received Christ in the sacrament or no.</title>
                  <author>Dyke, Jeremiah, 1584-1639.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 120 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by M. Simmons for John Rothwell at the signe of the Sunne in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Colossians II, 6-7 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153914:1"/>
            <p>THE RIGHT RECEIVING OF CHRIST.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OR, AN APPENDIX</hi> To the worthy COMMUNICANT, <hi>OR</hi> A Treatiſe ſhewing the due order of Receiving the SACRAMENT.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> JER. DYKE, Late Miniſter of <hi>Epping</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which was intended by the ſaid Author in his life time to be annexed to this Treatiſe of the Sacrament; as appeares in the Epiſtle.</p>
            <p>Wherein a Chriſtian may know, whether he hath rightly received Chriſt in the Sacrament or no.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed by <hi>M. Simmons</hi> for <hi>John Rothwell</hi> at the ſigne of the <hi>Sunne</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard.</p>
            <p>1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:153914:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153914:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F wee conſider the exceeding excellency of the whole Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, reſulting from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned and combined excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies of the ſeverall and various <hi>ſpecies</hi> of creatures, the leaſt we can doe is to admire; and who that admires the whole, can but obſerve this one particular as moſt remarkable? what creature it was which GOD the Creator wound up the Worlds perfection with; and that was man: Man, who though in regard of time, he was made the laſt of all, yet for ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude, the beſt of all, he being made after the Image of God himſelfe, for ſo was the Counſell and Decree of Heaven concerning him before he was made, and ſo alſo was the execution of that Decree when he was made.
<pb facs="tcp:153914:3"/> 
               <hi>So God created man in his own Image, in the Image of God created he him.</hi> The firſt gives him all the perfections of the reſt; the ſecond a perfection far above them all: The firſt gives him the poſſeſsion and uſe of all this whole inferiour world, being then as an houſe well furniſhed by God with all other ſublunary perfections, for the enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of man, and to be tenanted by him: the ſecond, that gives him Dominion <note place="margin">Gen. 1. 26.</note> and Lordſhip over all. And both of them ſhew, that as all things elſe were created for man, ſo man for God: then which, what high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er perfection could there be? and man thus made, made up the complement and perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the whole. Then God looking upon eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing that he had made, ſaw it not barely <hi>bonum,</hi> as before, but <hi>bonum valde,</hi> i. e. <note place="margin">Gen. 1. 31.</note> very good indeed: then alſo was man, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of all the other ſublunaries, as the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond to the Ring; not onely ſhining and glorious with the beſt excellencies of the more inferiour natures, but alſo glittering and ſparkling with the radiancie of his owne, and that as enriched with the divine, of which in a greater meaſure man at the firſt was made partaker: Man then was the choi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt
<pb facs="tcp:153914:3"/> plant of all that the Omnipotent hand of God had planted in that Garden of God where he was put; a right generous and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Vine. And had he then contented him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with that perfection and tranſcendent excellency of eſtate, which the all-wiſe God had thought fit, for that preſent to conferre upon him, paying duely his rent unto him, <hi>as he was made well able to doe;</hi> and doing this homage to him, in acknowledging him to be chiefe Lord of all, <hi>as it was very fit he ſhould have done;</hi> and bringing forth that acceptable fruit unto him, <hi>which he might have done;</hi> for he had in him the ſeed thereof: then might he have ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued without any change or alteration of eſtate, till at the laſt be had gathered to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and taſted the moſt delicious ſweetneſſe of the Fruit, not onely of all the other Trees (which for the preſent was allowed him) but alſo of that Tree growing in the midſt of the Garden by the Tree of knowledge of good and evill, even of the <hi>Tree of Life,</hi> and <note place="margin">Gen. 2. 9.</note> that not in the Figure, but in the ſubſtance; which thing he was by hope to have expected and waited for, till Gods time of his tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation or removall from an earthly to an Heavenly Paradiſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:153914:4"/>
            <p>But man, fooliſh man, aſpiring higher then was meet, and prepoſterouſly reaching after a condition above himſelfe, ſo at once, both fell ſhort of what he aym'd at, and of himſelfe; precipitantly falling from an higher excellency then he was any way wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of (in regard of ſo ill managing his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires) into a condition far below himſelfe. And ſo now againe you ſee him, who was once the beſt of all, become the very worſt of all; and him for whom once the whole Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion groaned (as labouring of imperfection till he was made) now by his ſin become a <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 22</note> burden which the whole Creation groaneth under: I may adde, and that no leſſe then ſuch as preſſeth under it the Creator of the <note place="margin">Amo. 2. 13. Iſa. 43. 24.</note> whole; yea, and by preſsing, wearieth him; him, whom once you ſaw Gods tenant to all, now you ſee diſcharged and turn'd out of all: he, who once, under God himſelfe (the chiefe Lord) had dominion over all, is now become the very drudge and ſlave of all, and not the ſlave of all the works of God alone, but which is worſt of all, the ſlave of ſin to his own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved and accurſed worke: him, whom once you ſaw the choiſeſt plant of all Gods hand, <hi>planted by him a noble Vine, and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Jer. 2. 21.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:153914:4"/> 
               <hi>a right ſeed unto himſelfe,</hi> you now ſee <hi>turned into the degenerate plant of a ſtrange Vine;</hi> a Vine like that the Prophet ſpeaks of, fit for no uſe at all but for a fire. And thus his greater happineſſe before, is now become his greater miſery, the higher perfection of that condition being but the lower defection of this; and the greater ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of the one, but the greater aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the other: in as much as from the higher pinacle that wee fall (you know) by ſo much the greater the hurt and danger that doth enſue.</p>
            <p>But is the miſery then ſo great, as that its paſt all cure and remedy? And is man, who thus had loſt himſelfe, quite loſt for ever? Yes, loſt for ever, and utterly remedileſſe in his miſery, for any thing at all that he can doe to helpe himſelfe: Yet God, not willing to loſe the Maſter-piece of all his works, and that the choiſeſt plant which his hand had planted, ſhould ſo miſcarry, then findes out a way to ſave him, who had loſt himſelfe; and to replant him, who by Satan had been ſo ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted: to which purpoſe therefore, he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth <hi>a root of Jeſſe</hi> to put forth, <hi>and to <note place="margin">Iſa. 11. 10. &amp; 53. 2.</note> grow up before him as a tender plant,
<pb facs="tcp:153914:5"/> and as a root out of a dry ground;</hi> into which ſtock or good Olive Tree, man ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated, <note place="margin">Ro. 11. 24.</note> might be ingraffed, and ſo reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his former nobleneſſe and generoſitie: his former nobleneſſe did I ſay? nay doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe I may be bold to ſay, that as God, to the effecting of this for man, ſhewed greater wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and mercy, then he before had done power and goodneſſe in making of him; ſo that it being once effected, he hath much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered his condition, and raiſed it to an high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er excellency then before; for though man in his firſt eſtate had in himſelfe a principle of life, and by that a ſeed of fruit anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to his preſent condition then, yet ſo as that it was wholly in his own keeping; like to a plant that grows upon its own bottome: yet now is life ſo in himſelfe, as that it is more in another, even in Chriſt, from whom (by vertue of union with him) as from a root or fountain he receives vivificall power and vigour continually to produce all ſpirituall and living actions, and to bring forth the fruits of holineſſe unto eternall life: even as the branch that lives not of it ſelfe, but hath all lively ſap and moiſture, both unto life and fruitfulneſſe, from the root or ſtock on which it grows: and ſo is our eſtate in Chriſt the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb facs="tcp:153914:5"/> 
               <hi>Adam,</hi> farre more ſecure and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous then ever it could have been in the firſt: beſides herein is the excellency of man in this condition, even above the Angels them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, in that Chriſt by aſſuming our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, hath thereby advanced it above theirs, <note place="margin">Heb. 2. 16.</note> which he never took upon him; in which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, man is now higher then thoſe glorious and celeſtiall Creatures, who at the firſt was made inferiour to them, though <hi>but a little</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 8. 5.</note> 
               <hi>lower then they.</hi> So that look what dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference there ſometimes was betwixt the firſt Temple and the ſecond; the very like may you ſee here betwixt theſe two conditions, if you compare them of man in <hi>Adam</hi> before his fall, as he was then by Creation, and of man ſince his fall, as he is now by Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Only there the former houſe did exceed in glory, and that ſo far, as <hi>the ancient men</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hag. 2. 3.</note> 
               <hi>of the Prieſts and Levites, which had ſeene the firſt, when they alſo ſaw the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ezr. 3. 12.</note> 
               <hi>laſt, could not but weepe with a lowd voyce</hi> to behold the difference; but here now the latter condition exceeds the former, in ſo much that they who ſhall once live to ſee, and experimentally to know the excellency of this above that, cannot but rejoyce with exceeding joy.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:153914:6"/>
            <p>And now <hi>(Chriſtian Reader)</hi> ſhould I here paſſe over in ſilence the farre more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding and tranſcendent excellency which is in Chriſt, (the fountaine of all that in the Saints excells in goodneſſe) I might ſeeme to obſcure what all this while I have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to cleare: for if their excellency in this renewed eſtate be not from him, then is it not ſo great an excellency as I have ſaid: But if it be derived all from him (as indeed it is) then ſhall I neither give him that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, which is his due, by being ſilent in ſuch a caſe; nor doe thee that right I ſhould, who by beholding of his beauty, mayſt perhaps be enamoured with it, and ſo the rather be brought to fall in love with him, in whom otherwiſe thou mayſt ſee <hi>no forme nor</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 53. 2.</note> 
               <hi>comelineſſe,</hi> nor any thing elſe <hi>that thou ſhouldſt deſire him.</hi> Tell me therefore:</p>
            <p>Is there nothing that thou canſt behold in Chriſt more amiable and lovely, then in the world? Is it nothing that while the world is a lump of vanity and meere vacui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1. Col. 1. 19.</note> yet that <hi>in him all fulneſſe dwels?</hi> fulneſſe in other things hath an attractive and invitatory vertue: the <hi>full garners</hi> drew <hi>Jacobs</hi> ſonnes downe into <hi>Aegypt;
<pb facs="tcp:153914:6"/> plentitude of wiſdome,</hi> the Queene of <hi>Sheba</hi> to King <hi>Salomon:</hi> and why doeſt thou covet the world, but from a delight <hi>de pleno tollere acervo,</hi> to take of a full heap? But alas! all this is emptineſſe to the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſt, who hath tranſcendently in him, all that this world affords. One little piece of gold is fuller of worth then many of ſilver, and one little Diamond then an heap of gold, all the petty perfections ſcattered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in the creatures, are in him united: that great volume of excellencies ſpread up and downe through Heaven and Earth, is in him epitomiz'd: beſides that fulneſſe of Grace, of which the world hath not a dram. The world, at the fulleſt, is but an Ocean which is leſſened by loſing the leaſt drop; but Chriſt his fulneſſe, is the fulneſſe of fire, which is not one jot diminiſhed, though it gives light to a thouſand Torches. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall effluences of vertue out of him, and influences of the ſap of his quickning grace, into all thoſe fruit-bearing branches (though infinite in number) that draw from him, is not the leaſt evacuation at all unto him.</p>
            <p>Is it nothing, that while the creature doth allure us from God, our own guilty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences,
<pb facs="tcp:153914:7"/> and the dreadfulneſſe of his glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Majeſty deterre us; Chriſt onely drawes us to him (who is the chiefeſt and only good,) ſo that <hi>through him alone we have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eph. 2. 18.</note> 
               <hi>unto the Father?</hi> God is a Sunne, the reſplendent beames of whoſe Majeſty, ſo glorious an object, would overcharge, and even quite put out thoſe preſumptuous eyes, that ſhould dare to looke up to him, unleſſe overcaſt with the Cloud of Chriſt a Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour. God is a conſuming fire, and mortall were it for us mortalls, to come neere it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the interpoſed Skreene of Chriſt his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation. Firſt muſt wee come to the manger of Chriſts humanity, before we can have an acceſſe with boldneſſe to the Throne of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Majeſty.</p>
            <p>Is it nothing, that while the world, in our greateſt exigents, ſues out a divorce, and then deſerts us, yet that Chriſt is conſtant in his love, having once tyed himſelfe to us with the knot of conjugall affection, which with him is indiſſoluble? Chriſt is our huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band: And hence, how many precious privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges enſured to us? In law <hi>uxori lis non intenditur;</hi> what then hath the law, exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obedience unto life, to doe with Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans?
<pb facs="tcp:153914:7"/> Againe, <hi>Mulier fulget radiis mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti:</hi> The Husband communicates all that he hath unto his Wife: and even ſuch a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity of grace is there betwixt Chriſt and true beleevers; Chriſt his graces and a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers differing onely <hi>ſecundum gradum,</hi> i. e. in reſpect of meaſure or degree; but not at all <hi>ſecundum ſpeciem,</hi> i. e. in kinde or quality, in which reſpect they are the ſame.</p>
            <p>Beſides all which, are all the benefits of our myſticall union with Chriſt, nothing? Hence ſpirituall life: Hence conformitie <note place="margin">Col. 3. 3. 4. Rom. 6. 5. 1 Pet. 1. 14. Phil. 2. 5. 1 Joh. 2. 6. Joh. 15. 5. Rom. 8. 35.</note> with Chriſt our head, a triple conformity, in nature, in minde, in converſation: Hence fructification for the preſent: Hence perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance for the future, even to the end: Hence glorification alſo in the end; yea, and therein admiſsion of our bodies as well as ſoules into eternall glory at the laſt. And is all this to be accounted nothing?</p>
            <p>Many, and many are the excellencies to be found in Chriſt, and to be received from him, which (beſides theſe that I have men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned) I might inſtance in, and ſo lead thee ſtill on forward in this way, even till I ſhould, as in a maze or labyrinth, loſe both
<pb facs="tcp:153914:8"/> my ſelfe and thee, in the contemplation of them: But becauſe I had much rather, that thou ſhouldſt be found in Chriſt, then loſt in the contemplation of Chriſt; and becauſe my hearty deſire is for thee, that thou ſhouldſt be more a reall Chriſtian, and eſtated in him, then contemplative, and alwayes onely meditating of him; as an excellent meanes therefore amongst many others, to help thee in, and guide thee to the <hi>Right Receiving</hi> of, and <hi>rooting</hi> in Chriſt, I can now for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare no longer, to commend unto thy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſall this following <hi>Treatiſe:</hi> Not a packe of Brachygraphicall fragments, and incohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ſcraps, jumbled together by ſome prag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall pen man; but a worke (upon my certaine knowledge) perfectly finiſhed, and that purpoſely for the Preſſe, by the learned and moſt judicious Pen of my <hi>Moſt deare</hi> and <hi>late deceaſed Father,</hi> and then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by him to have been annexed, as an <hi>Appendix</hi> to that laſt worke of his, which himſelfe publiſhed before his death, entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>A worthy Communicant, Or a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe ſhewing the due order of receiving the Sacrament, &amp;c.</hi> and this a Treatiſe, intituled, <hi>The Right Receiving of, and
<pb facs="tcp:153914:8"/> Rooting in Chriſt;</hi> the very Title which he himſelfe did put upon it while he lived. Which fore-named Treatiſe (Chriſtian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) with all his <hi>Former Works</hi> by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe publiſhed (that gracious acceptance which they ever found from thee, and the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and honour I ſtill doe, and ſhall ever owe to him) made me thus farre to deny my ſelfe, as to adventure (though but a bungler at it) to afford my obſtretricatory aſsiſtance to this Poſthumus Infant, rather then it ſhould al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes lye gaſping in the Preſſe, ready to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh for want of helpe.</p>
            <p>To ſpeak any thing in the commendations of this Work, its own mouth denyes me; and is the rather needleſſe, in that I have now ſo farre aſſur'd thee of its Author, who himſelfe had thus finiſht it for thy uſe, as thou now receiv'ſt it.</p>
            <p>To ſpeak much of the Author, modeſty and my neere relation to him, will not admit of; and to ſay nothing of him, duty forbids me: With the leave of modeſty then will I ſpeake thus much onely and no more; and if any ſhall thinke I ſay too much, I will leave it to duty to excuſe me. For his Fidelity and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiality in the Work of his Miniſtery, who
<pb facs="tcp:153914:9"/> knew him, and knowes not, that the Sword of the Spirit was in his hands, a two-edged Sword, which cut every way? not like <hi>Sauls,</hi> that cut off the leane and worſt of the people and cattell, and ſpared <hi>Agag</hi> and the fatteſt cattell; but like the Pſalmiſts Sword, which ſpared none. Yet ſo, as that alwayes mens ſinnes, not their perſons, were the objects of his hotteſt thunder-bolts.</p>
            <p>I will here paſſe by his rare accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with all Miniſteriall abilities, as bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter knowne, then that I need to mention them. <hi>Alii pleni, &amp; non loquuntur, hi non pleni, loquuntur: Alii multiſcii, &amp; muti; hi ignari, &amp; ſonori.</hi> How he was every way free from both theſe Miniſteriall defects, thou who know'ſt him not in the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, reade him in the Preſſe, and judge.</p>
            <p>For his indefatigabilitie in his labours, and all for other mens eternall profit, more then his own private and worldly benefit, he was one of Saint <hi>Chryſoſtoms</hi> Bees, <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſiſſimum animal,</hi> not becauſe it labours, but becauſe its labour is to others profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>And for his inoffenſive life, who knowes not that he was none of thoſe ſlimy Lizards,
<pb facs="tcp:153914:9"/> who wipe out the wholeſome Print of their Doctrine, with the filthy tayle of their ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous practiſes.</p>
            <p>But here now, though Modeſty did not, yet the Father would take me off, who tells me, now God hath taken the Arke of his bleſſed ſoule out of the moveable earthly Tabernacle of his body, and placed it in the fixed Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of celeſtiall bliſſe, <hi>Imitationem quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> 
               <hi>non laudes,</hi> that my beſt commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will be imitation. While he lived, God honoured him to be one of <hi>Gideons</hi> Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, who carried both a Trumpet and a Lampe; the Trumpet of his Miniſtery he let fall, and the light of his practiſe wee all loſt when God cracked aſunder his earthen Pitcher. The greateſt honour I can now doe him, is not to Trumpet forth his praiſes, and make a blaze with his commendations; but to take up both the Trumpet and Lampe which he laid downe, in an holy imitation of him, both in ſoundneſſe of Doctrine, and piety of practiſe: and in this caſe I am ſure, what duty commands me, that Modeſty will not forbid.</p>
            <p>And thus, that God would not onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow the mantle, but double the ſpirit of this
<pb facs="tcp:153914:10"/> deceaſed <hi>Eliah,</hi> upon his ſurviving poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, be it thy daily Petition at the Throne of Grace; and to requite thee, that God would redouble a bleſsing of his ſervants Labours upon thy pious endeavours, ſhall be the humble Supplication of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>The Churches devoted Servant,</salute>
            </closer>
            <signed>JER. DYKE.</signed>
         </div>
         <div type="contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:153914:66"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> It is the dutie of every one that will be a Chriſtian, to receive Chriſt. <hi>fol.</hi> 6.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Ignorance of the worth of Chriſt, keepes men from receiving him. 9.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> The great benefit that comes by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of Chriſt. 13.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:153914:67"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> The great danger of not Receiving Chriſt. 26</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Hindrances to be removed by ſuch as would Receive Chriſt. 32</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> The love of our luſts, a hindrance from receiving Chriſt. 37</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Falſe and groundleſs feares, a hindrance to the receiving of Chriſt. 41</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> The Poſitive Duty which muſt be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of all that will receive Chriſt. 46</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:153914:71"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> How to know whether wee have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Chriſt aright. 62</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Whoſoever they are that have indeed received Chriſt, they doe walke in him. 75</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> Trialls of Mens Receiving of Chriſt. 80</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> It is a Chriſtians Dutie to walke in Chriſt. 84</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> It is not enough for a Chriſtian to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, and beare the Name of Chriſt, but he muſt be Rooted in him. 89</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:153914:72"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIIII.</hi> What is to be done that wee may get our ſelves to be Rooted in Chriſt. 104</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> How to know whether wee be Rooted in Chriſt, or not. 115</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153914:10"/>
            <head>THE RIGHT RECEIVING OF AND ROOTING IN CHRIST.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>COLOS. 2. 6, 7.</bibl>
               <q>As yee have therefore received the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, ſo walke yee in him, Rooted in him.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the former Chapter, <hi>v.</hi> 23. the Apoſtle entred upon an Exhortation to perſeverance in the faith. In the firſt ſeven verſes of this chapter he continues that exhortation, laying down more <hi>reaſons,</hi> and removing <hi>objections.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. He layes downe reaſons to preſſe them; And they are ſpecially two.</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:153914:11"/>
               <item>1. <hi>The firſt</hi> taken from his owne care that he had for their, and others good, <hi>ver.</hi> 1, 2.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>The ſecond</hi> taken from the certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſublimity, and perfection of the Goſpel, <hi>ver.</hi> 2, 3.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="2">2. He removes <hi>Objections.</hi> What needs all this adoe with us? might the <hi>Coloſsians</hi> ſay. <hi>Anſw.</hi> I would have you conſtrue it to be done out of a loving feare and jealouſie, leſt any ſhould ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce and wrong you, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. I, but is not this an unchriſtian ſuſpition in you, thus haſtily to ſurmiſe the worſt by us? might they reply. <hi>Anſw.</hi> No ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for I doe with great joy behold and acknowledge that great good that is in, and amongſt you, <hi>ver.</hi> 5. Well then, what is it that you would have us doe? <hi>Anſw.</hi> Since my care is ſo great for you, ſince the Goſpel is ſo certaine, ſublime and perfect, therefore I would have you, That <hi>as you have received Chriſt,</hi> ſo yee <hi>would walke on in him, &amp;c.</hi> In which words, he exhorteth them unto two things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. To walke in Chriſt.</item>
               <item>2. To be rooted in him.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:153914:11"/>
            <p>To a going on in the profeſſion of Chriſt, and to a ſtability, and ſtedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe there in.</p>
            <p>Hee firſt exhorts to a walking in Chriſt. To this he urges them by that they had already done. <hi>As yee have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Chriſt Jeſus the Lord.</hi> As if he had ſaid, Yee have begun well, yee have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Chriſt the Lord, and yee profeſſe yee have received him, now then as yee have begun, ſo goe on, and to your re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiving of Chriſt, adde your going on, and walking in him; from which argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Apoſtle, we may take this leſſon by the way:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That good beginnings are an engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Doct.</note> 
               <hi>to good proceedings.</hi> Receiving Chriſt is an engagement and an obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to walking in him, <hi>Pſal. 4. 9. Thoſe things that yee have both learned, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and heard, and ſeene in me, doe.</hi> Thus you have learned, and received, therefore doe thus. <hi>Apoc. 3. 3. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber therefore how thou haſt received, and heard, and hold faſt and repent.</hi> It is this ground that edges thoſe ſharp reproofs, <hi>Gal. 3. 3. Are yee ſo fooliſh? Having be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153914:12"/> in the Spirit, are yee now made perfect by the fleſh?</hi> and <hi>Gal. 5. 7. Yee did run well, who did hinder you that you ſhould not obey the truth?</hi> And this is the reaſon why they that have begun well, and yet goe not on, ſhall receive a ſmarter puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then ſuch as never made any ſuch beginning at all, becauſe they had a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter tye and engagement then others to be godly, and religious. <hi>Their latter end is worſe then their beginning,</hi> 2 Pet. 2. 20. And why ſo? becauſe their beginnings were better then other mens. They be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to build, they began to look towards Chriſt and Heaven, theſe beginnings engaged them to a further progreſſe, and becauſe ſuch engagement, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they brake off, therefore have they made their account the heavier.</p>
            <p>Let it teach us therefore if once wee have given up our names to Chriſt, to goe on, and hold on. A giving up the name to Chriſt, and a beginning to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe religion, it is a <hi>ſubſcribing</hi> with the hand to the Lord. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44. 5. It is a ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>I am the Lords.</hi> Now when wee have once ſaid we are the Lords, and have
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153914:12"/> ſubſcribed to it, ſet us alſo have a care to ſay, wee will be the Lords, and to ſtand to, and make good our ſubſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But if once wee have ſubſcribed with our hand, and after our ſubſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be found Revolters, God will bring in our own hands againſt us. The en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance upon profeſſion of Chriſts name is ſubſcription; Subſcription is an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation to God. An obligation forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted makes a man liable to the penalty. This by the way. Before I come to the thing preſſed, I will take the words in order as they lye, and begin firſt with that ground upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which he preſſes them to that duty. <hi>As yee have received Jeſus Chriſt the Lord.</hi> In which words he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes that they had received Chriſt, they profeſſed that they had received him, and he takes it for granted, as a ground upon which he will work them on further; from what theſe <hi>Coloſsians</hi> did, learne <hi>What is every mans duty to doe, that meanes to be a true Chriſtian in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:153914:13"/>
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>It is the duty of every one that will be a Chriſtian, to receive Chriſt.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>A Man is never a Chriſtian indeed till this be done. The Lord Jeſus Chriſt is to be received of us. God he offers Chriſt to us, he tenders him in the Goſpel, and as it is Gods <hi>mercy</hi> to offer him, ſo it is our <hi>duty,</hi> and ſhould be our wiſdome to receive him; for that is the end of all Gods offers. He doth not offer him only to ſhew that there is a Chriſt, or what kinde of Chriſt he is, hee doth not offer him to be ſeen, and ſhewed, but God offers him to this end, that he might be received. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when God ſends his Miniſters to preach Chriſt, and to offer him unto people in their miniſtery, hee ſpeaks of Chriſt in this caſe, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks to the <hi>Philippians</hi> of <hi>Epaphroditus,</hi> Phil. 2. 29. <hi>Receive him with all gladneſſe, and hold him in reputation.</hi> And as God offers Chriſt to be received, ſo he himſelf alſo is willing to be received. Wee know
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153914:13"/> what the Phariſees quarrell was with him, <hi>Luke 15. 2. This man receives ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</hi> And it was true hee did ſo. But why did he ſo? Surely to let ſinners ſee how willing hee is that they ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him. His receiving of ſinners was but to invite them to the receiving of him. Yea, the errand he ſends his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters upon, is but to perſwade men to receive him. Hee ſeeks to be received, <hi>Cant. 5. 2. Open unto mee my ſiſter, my love,</hi> &amp;c. As if he had ſaid, Lo, here I am, I offer my ſelf unto thee, I ſue and ſeek unto thee to be received and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. Yea, hee complains of it, and takes it ill, when men receive him not, <hi>John 5. 43. I came in my Fathers Name, and yee received me not.</hi> Now if Chriſt were not willing, and deſirous to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, he would not complain of it, and take it as an unkindneſs not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived. Wee ought in their kind to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive godly men, <hi>John 3. 8. We therefore ought to receive ſuch.</hi> And if we ought to receive ſuch, then much more ought we to receive Chriſt himſelf.</p>
               <p>As then wee would prove our ſelves <note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe 1.</note>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:153914:14"/> true Chriſtians indeed, ſo be we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and ready to receive Chriſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered unto us. Wee ſhould do in this caſe as <hi>Zacheus</hi> did in that, <hi>Luke 19. 5, 6. Zacheus,</hi> ſayes Chriſt, <hi>Make haſte, and come down, for to day I muſt abide at thine houſe.</hi> Here was an offer, a fair offer of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> What doth <hi>Zacheus</hi> do? does he demurre and deliberate upon it, and take time to think of it? no ſuch matter, <hi>And he made haſt,</hi> ſayes the Text, <hi>and came down, and</hi> received <hi>him joyfully. Zacheus</hi> preſently imbraces the offer, &amp; receives him haſtily, and joyfully. No ſooner ſhould Chriſt offer himſelf unto us, but with all readines &amp; greedines ſhould he be received of us: There is a ſtrange per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeneſſe of ſpirit in us, a ſtrange na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall untowardneſſe in us to receive Chriſt: See how Chriſt ſpeaks, <hi>Joh. 5. 43. I am come unto you in my Fathers name, and yee receive me not; if another come in his own name, him yee will receive.</hi> So it is ſtill with us: If Satan come with a tentation, if a luſt come with a motion, if a falſe teacher come with a novelty, if any thing come that ſhould not come, it
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153914:14"/> is ſtrange to ſee with what readines and greedines we receive theſe: but if Chriſt come, with whom comes all good, how awke, and how backward are we to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him? Men bleſſe themſelves with coming to Church, and receivng the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and think all is well ſo long as this is done: But how many come to Church that come not to Chriſt, and how many receive the Sacrament, that yet receive not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt? This therefore being a point of ſo great conſequence, and neceſſity as none grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; it will not be amiſſe to help to ſink it down with ſome conſiderations, as may make way for it into our hearts. Conſider therefore theſe three things.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ignorance</hi> of the worth of Chriſt, keeps men from receiving him.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>FIrſt,</hi> conſider who it is that is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived. It is <hi>Jeſus Chriſt the Lord,</hi> ſays the Text. He in whom is all our good, and by whom we have all ſpirituall, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153914:15"/> eternall good that is to be had. How gladly do ſome receive Lords, great ones, how gladly do men receive Kings? Now Chriſt, he is the Lord, the King of Glory. Upon this ground are we exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to receive him: <hi>Pſal. 24. 7. 9. Lift up your heads, O yee gates, and be yee lift up yee everlaſting doors,</hi> that is, lift up your hearts, and ſet the doors of your hearts wide open. But why, what ſhall we get by it? <hi>The King of glory ſhall enter.</hi> So that when the King of Glory is to be received, how readily ſhould men ſet their hearts wide open to receive him? Receive Chriſt, and yee receive the King of Glory, and the King of Glory enters. The Apoſtle preſſing to hoſpitality, uſes this argument, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13. 2. that ſome thereby received Angells. Oh, how glad would a man be, to have ſuch gueſts as <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Lot</hi> had? how glad would a man be to receive Angels? I, but here is a greater matter. In receiving Chriſt, we receive not An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, but wee receive the Son of God himſelf, not into our houſes, but into our hearts. What be Angels to the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153914:15"/> King of Glory, to the Son of God? If men did but conſider, who it is that ſhould be received, and what a gueſt they ſhould receive, when they receive Chriſt, how eaſily would they be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to receive him? Men know not Chriſt, know not his worth and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie, and therefore receive him not, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 10, 11. That which is in one verſe, <hi>Knew him not,</hi> is in the other, <hi>Receive him not:</hi> To ſhew that men therefore receive not Chriſt, becauſe they know him not, they know not how precious a Chriſt he is. Oh, how gladly and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily would men receive him, if once they knew who, and what he were? We find, <hi>John</hi> 6. 19. that the Diſciples not knowing Chriſt, were afraid of him, though he came towards them, yet they were ſo farre from receiving him, that they would well have wiſht him further off. Being afraid of him, they muſt needs be afraid to receive him. But when, <hi>verſe</hi> 20. Chriſt makes himſelf known unto them, <hi>It is I, be not afraid;</hi> then <hi>verſe 21. They willingly received him into the ſhip.</hi> When once they knew
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153914:16"/> it was Chriſt whom they ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, they then no longer feare, but willingly and gladly receive him. So when Chriſt is offered unto men they receive him not, becauſe they know him not, and therfore indeed are many times afraid to receive him. They think if he be received, they may loſe their credit and friends in the world; that this Chriſt will mar all the joy and pleaſure of their lives, and that they ſhould lead but melancholy mopiſh lives; and ſo not knowing Chriſt, are afraid of him. I, but it is the Lord Chriſt that is offered unto you, the Lord of life, and grace, the Lord of all comfort and conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; it is a Saviour and Redeemer that is offered unto you; It is that Chriſt that dyed for you, that ſhed his blood for you, that did undergo the curſe of God, and bare the infinite weight of his Fathers wrath to deliver you; It is a <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> a ſaving Chriſt who is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered unto you. Since therefore it is Chriſt, and he ſuch a Chriſt, this ſhould make us receive him, and receive him as willingly into our hearts, as they
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153914:16"/> when they knew him, received him into the ſhip; It is the Lord Jeſus Chriſt that is offered us, be yee then lift up yee everlaſting doors, fly open yee gates of our hearts, that Jeſus Chriſt the Lord may be received and entertained. How gladly did the <hi>Galatians</hi> receive <hi>Paul</hi> who was but a Miniſter, and an Apoſtle of Chriſt? <hi>Gal. 4. 14. Yee received me as an Angel of God, even as Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> If they ſo received a Miniſter of Chriſt, how then ſhould Chriſt Jeſus himſelf be received?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The great <hi>benefit</hi> that comes by receiving Chriſt.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>SEcondly,</hi> Conſider the great benefit we ſhall receive by receiving Chriſt, we ſhall be ſure to be on the receiving hand by receiving Chriſt. It is a great advantage wee receive to our ſelves by receiving Chriſt into our hearts. There is a great reward to be received in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving a Prophet, nay, in receiving
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153914:17"/> an ordinary righteous man, <hi>Matth. 10. 41. He that receives a Prophet, in the name of a Prophet, ſhall receive a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets reward; hee that receives a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous man in the name of a righteous man, ſhall receive a righteous mans reward.</hi> In the 40. <hi>verſe,</hi> our Saviour ſpeaks of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving himſelf, <hi>Hee that receiveth you receiveth mee.</hi> Now if ſuch a reward to him that receives a Prophet, if ſuch a reward to him that receives a righteous man, how much more ſhall that man, that ſoul be richly bleſſed and rewarded that receives Chriſt Jeſus the Lord, the Prophet of the Church, and that great Righteous One? Let us a little then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Reward of receiving Chriſt, what it is, and what benefit will follow thereupon. There is a three-fold Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward or Benefit that followes upon it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The firſt</hi> Benefit is the Adoption of ſons and daughters. They that receive Chriſt ſhall thereupon receive this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and happineſſe, to be made ſons of God. <hi>Seems it a ſmall thing unto you to be the Kings ſon in Law?</hi> ſaith <hi>David</hi> to the ſervants of <hi>Saul.</hi> And if it be no
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:153914:17"/> ſmall thing to be the Kings ſon in Law, then it is no ſmall honour to be Gods ſonnes and daughters, 1 <hi>Joh. 3. 1. Behold, what love the Father hath ſhewed unto us, that wee ſhould be called the ſonnes of God.</hi> It was the greateſt love that God could ſhew us, the greateſt honour that God could doe us, to make us his ſonnes. But now how come wee to receive this great honour? We receive this honour by receiving Chriſt. They that receive Chriſt, receive this honour to be the ſonnes of God, <hi>John 1. 12. To as many as</hi> received him <hi>he gave this priviledge to become the ſonnes of God.</hi> As many as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him. What ever they were for outward condition, rich or poore, bond or free, high or low, old or young, if they received him, they loſt nothing by it; Chriſt thereupon gave them this honour, to be made the ſonnes of God. The Apoſtle twice ſpeakes of the great priviledge of Chriſtians, <hi>Rom. 8. 15. Yee have received the Spirit of Adoption.</hi> Gal. 4. 4, 5. <hi>That wee might receive the Adoption of ſonnes.</hi> I, but how come wee to receive the Adoption of ſonnes?
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:153914:18"/> 
                  <hi>God ſent his Sonne that wee might receive the Adoption of ſonnes.</hi> But is that all that is to be done that God ſhould ſend his Sonne? No, for though God hath ſent his Son, yet all are not made ſons. Therefore as on Gods part, ſo ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is to be done on our part alſo, God ſent forth his Sonne that we might receive his Sonne, and ſo might receive the Adoption of ſonnes: <hi>For to as many</hi> as received him, <hi>he gave them this privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to be made the Sons of God.</hi> Luk. 19. 9. This day, is <hi>Zacheus become a ſonne of Abraham.</hi> It is all one to be a ſonne of <hi>Abraham</hi> in our Saviours ſenſe, and a ſonne of God. Now when became <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus</hi> a ſonne of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and ſo a ſonne of God? <hi>This day,</hi> namely, in which he had received Chriſt, not onely into his houſe, but into his heart. The very ſame day, and houre then that a man receives Chriſt into his heart, that very day and houre he receives the honour and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe of being a ſonne of God. When we receive Chriſt, God receives us, and when he receives us, wee receive the great benefit of Adoption. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 17,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:153914:18"/> 18. <hi>I will receive you.</hi> And what ſhall we receive by that? <hi>And will be a Father un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, and yee ſhall be my ſonnes and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſaith the Lord God Almighty.</hi> Now what a motive is this, if well conſidered, to make us receive Chriſt? It may be for thine outward eſtate thou art but the ſonne of meane parents, of poore obſcure parents, it may be in a ſervile and bond condition. Or what ever thou art for thine outward, yet for thy ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall condition, thou art naturally no better then a childe of wrath, a childe of death, a curſed childe, a ſlave of the devill, a baſe drudge to thy luſts. And were it not now a faire advancement, a goodly and a glorious priviledge for ſuch an one to be made a ſon of God? why then, doe but receive Chriſt, and he will preſently honour thee with this priviledge, to be made a ſonne of God, <hi>Gal. 3. 7. Know yee therefore that they which are of faith,</hi> and ſo by faith doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Chriſt, <hi>the ſame are the Children of Abraham,</hi> yea, know yee, that they which receive Chriſt, the ſame are the children of God. <hi>Gal. 3. 26, 27. Yee are the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:153914:19"/> of God by faith.</hi> Why ſo? <hi>Becauſe yee have put on Chriſt.</hi> He that puts on Chriſt receives him, as he that puts on a garment receives it. So that by faith putting on, and receiving Chriſt, we are made the ſonnes of God. Had wee but hearts to conſider, and in ſome ſort but to conceive, what it is to be a damned dog, a ſon of wrath, and what it is to be a ſonne of God, how would our ſoules not almoſt but altogether be perſwaded to receive Chriſt? If the receiving of the Kings ſonne would make us but the Kings favourites, how ambitious would we be, and at what coſt to receive him, if but an opportunity offered? But here now doe but receive Chriſt, and thou ſhalt be not onely one of Gods favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, but one of Gods ſonnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſecond</hi> benefit, is the Spirit of God. There is a promiſe, <hi>Act. 2. 38. Yee ſhall receive the gift of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> It is a bleſſed thing to receive the Holy Ghoſt. He is the Spirit of life, and light, the ſpirit of conſolation, power, and prayer. So that the receiving of the Spirit of God is the receiving of all
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:153914:19"/> ſpirituall good, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 32. 15. where the Spirit of God is powred forth, the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe becomes a fruitfull field. And there is thriving, and growing in Grace, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44. 3. It were needleſſe to inſiſt in all the benefits we have by receiving the Holy Ghoſt. Conſider that 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 10. 12. But now how come wee to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Holy Ghoſt? By Receiving Chriſt; The Receiving of Chriſt is the way to receive the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>Gal. 3. 14. That wee might receive the promiſe of the Spirit through faith.</hi> Through faith wee receive Chriſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 12. and through that receiving of Chriſt by faith, we alſo receive the Spirit. <hi>Joh. 7. 39. This be ſpake of the Spirit which they that beleeve in him ſhould receive.</hi> When Chriſt once is in us, and dwells in us, we have received him, as he that dwells in an houſe is received thereinto. And <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 9, 10, 11. The Apoſtle ſhewes that by Chriſts being in us, we have the Spirit in us. As we know, <hi>when Chriſt gives us his Spirit, that he dwells in us, 1 Joh.</hi> 4. 13. ſo we know alſo that when he dwells in us, he gives us his Spirit.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:153914:20"/> It is not every mans caſe to have Gods Spirit. As all men have not faith, ſo all men have not the Spirit of God. Every one receives him not, every one cannot receive him, <hi>Joh. 14. 17. The Spirit of Truth, whom the world cannot receive;</hi> And what is the reaſon why worldly men cannot receive him? Becauſe they will not receive Chriſt. Chriſt muſt be firſt received, before his Spirit can be received, for the Spirit is Chriſts Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and therefore muſt he be received before his Spirit can. No ſooner is Chriſt received, but he breaths upon that ſoule that receives him, and ſayes unto it, as he did in that caſe to his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, <hi>Receive the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> When <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magus</hi> ſaw, that by laying on of the Apoſtles hands, men received the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, he would preſently have been drawing his purſe, and would have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven money to have had that gift, <hi>Act.</hi> 8. 17, 18, 19. Now if wee would have the bleſſing our ſelves to receive the Holy Ghoſt, wee ſhall not need to ſeek it by money, that will not doe it. It muſt be had not by <hi>Giving,</hi> but by <hi>Receiving.</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:153914:20"/> Receive Chriſt, and his Spirit is ours. Marke how the Apoſtle carries thoſe words, <hi>Rom. 13. 13, 14. Let us walk ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly, as in the day, not in rioting, drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, &amp;c. But put yee on the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</hi> One would have thought he ſhould have ſaid, But put on the Graces of ſobriety, chaſtity, love, &amp;c. and all the graces of the Spirit, but in ſtead of that he ſayes, <hi>put yee on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> becauſe the putting on of Chriſt, and receiving of him, is the putting on, and the receiving of the Spirit, and all the ſanctifying graces thereof. If then we prize the receiving of the Spirit of grace into our hearts, then with all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe receive we Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The third</hi> benefit is Power and Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <note place="margin">3.</note> to yeeld God obedience. In recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Chriſt we do withall receive power and ability to give God obedience. He requires of us duties of obedience, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of worſhip, as hearing, prayer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He requires of us to work the works of God, and to walk in the wayes of God. Now take us in our ſelves, and wee can do nothing: till we have received Chriſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:153914:21"/> we can do no duty of obedience, of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, we can neither walk, nor work. But when Chriſt is once received into the ſoul, then there is withall a power re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into the ſoul, by which it is ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to do the duties God requires of us: See how theſe are joyned together in this Text, <hi>As yee have received Chriſt Jeſus the Lord, ſo walk in him.</hi> Wee are commanded to walk in him, but yet we muſt receive him. A man that will walk, muſt firſt receive a principle of life and motion. A dead man can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther walke nor worke; wee are made alive before wee do walk, and wee are made alive by receiving Chriſt, 1 <hi>Joh. 5. 12. Hee that hath the Son hath life.</hi> Hee that hath received Chriſt hath received life, by which he is enabled to actions of life, <hi>Gal. 2. 20. The life which I now live in the fleſh, I live by the faith of the Son of God,</hi> as if hee had ſaid; I have received Chriſt, and ſo having received him, have alſo received ſpirituall life by which I am quickened and enabled to all duties of obedience, <hi>Gal. 5. 25. If wee live in the Spirit, let us alſo walk in the Spirit:</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:153914:21"/> And if we would walk in the Spirit, we muſt live in the Spirit: and ſo, if wee would walk in Chriſt, we muſt firſt live in Chriſt, and live by Chriſt. It is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for us to live, till wee have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Chriſt, who is our life. The Apoſtle here ſpeaks of <hi>walking in Chriſt, 2 Cor.</hi> 6. 16. he ſpeaks of <hi>Chriſts walking in us,</hi> I will dwell in them, <hi>and walk in them.</hi> It is a ſure thing, that hee muſt <hi>walk in us,</hi> before wee can <hi>walk in him.</hi> And hee cannot walk in us, till wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him: <hi>Joh. 15. Without me,</hi> or ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from me, <hi>yee can do nothing.</hi> Now till wee receive him wee are ſeparated from him. But now let us once receive him, and wee receive power to do what he requires. When <hi>Adam</hi> lay a lump of clay on the earth, though his body had the ſhape, parts, and proportion of a man, yet could hee do no action be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to a man till he received life. But ſo ſoon as he received life, he could walk, ſpeak, diſcourſe, do any thing that belonged to a man. So though a man in his naturall condition may do morall duties of obedience, and perform out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:153914:22"/> ſervices, yet all this while this is but the liveleſſe ſhape of a Chriſtian. But when once he receives Chriſt, who is our life, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. then Chriſtian life is infuſed, and received, and then hee can do ſuch things as a Chriſtian doth them, with that power and ſpirit that is required in a Chriſtian. It is little com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort we can have in any thing we do, or have, till wee have received Chriſt, and do what wee do by his power. Then a man hath comfort in the fruits of his obedience, when it is fruit unto God. Then our fruit is brought forth to God when we bring it forth by vertue of our marriage to Chriſt. <hi>Rom. 7. 4. That yee ſhould be married to Chriſt, that we ſhould bring forth fruit unto God.</hi> A woman may have children that is not married, but ſhee can have little credit and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in ſuch fruit of her wombe; It is but baſtardly fruit, upon which ſhee cannot look without bluſhing cheekes: but then hath ſhee comfort in her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, when they are legitimate, and ſhee hath them by her husband in marriage. Turkes and Heathens may doe ſome
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:153914:22"/> morall duties of Juſtice, mercy, &amp;c. but it is all but ſpurious fruit, baſe-born iſſue, in which they can have no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, becauſe all theſe are children out of lawfull wedlock, they are not mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in Chriſt, and bring not forth by a principle of life from him. What a motive ſhould this be to make us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Chriſt? Wee are in a miſerable condition, till we do receive him. God commands to repent, and we know that without repentance there is no way but damnation; <hi>Except yee repent, yee ſhall all periſh.</hi> God commands to mortifie the deeds of the fleſh, and wee know that without mortification there is no way but death, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 13. Now untill wee receive Chriſt, wee can as well remove mountaines, as repent for one ſinne, as mortifie one luſt. But when Chriſt is once received, then is power received to mortifie luſts, then there is power received to repent, <hi>Act. 5. 13. Him hath God exalted to be a Prince, and a Saviour, for to give repentance to Iſrael.</hi> As there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we deſire to receive power and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility to give God obedience, and to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:153914:23"/> performe the duties of his ſervice he requires, ſo be ready and forward to receive Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The great <hi>danger</hi> of not Receiving Chriſt.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>THirdly,</hi> Conſider the great Danger of not Receiving Chriſt. It is a <note place="margin">3.</note> wonderfull dangerous thing not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Chriſt when God offers him, and when he ſeekes to us, and invites us to receive him. It is a great ſinne not to receive Chriſt, <hi>Joh. 5. 43. Yee receive me not. John</hi> complaines, 3 <hi>John</hi> 9. 10. that <hi>Diotrephes received him not, and that he received not the brethren.</hi> This is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of as a great ſin. And if a great ſinne in <hi>Diotrephes</hi> not to receive <hi>John,</hi> and not to receive the brethren, how much more is it a great ſinne not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Chriſt? ſpecially when he offers himſelf to be received of us? It is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of as the hainous and horrible ſinne of the Jewes, <hi>Joh. 1. 11. That he came to his owne, and his own received him
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:153914:23"/> not.</hi> It was the foule ſin of the world, that when Chriſt as God was in the world, and the world was made by him, that the world knew him not, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 10. but it is made the greater ſinne of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> that when he was manifeſted in the fleſh, and he came to them in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and offered himſelfe to them, yet they received him not. And our ſinne now under the more cleere light of the Goſpel, will be greater then theirs if we receive him not. And as the ſinne is great, ſo muſt the danger and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it needs be great, if we receive him not. They to whom Chriſt is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, if they receive him not, it may be ſaid of them in this caſe, as our Saviour ſpeaks of the Phariſees in that, <hi>Luk. 20. 47. They ſhall receive the greater Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> There is a greater Damnation for ſome men then for other ſome. There is Damnation for ſuch as know not God, and never heard of Chriſt, but for thoſe that have heard of Chriſt, and have had him offered unto them, and have refuſed, and not received that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered Chriſt, there is a greater Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:153914:24"/> If men receive not ſo <hi>great ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> Heb. 2. 3. as is offered by receiving Chriſt, how ſhall they but receive the <hi>greater Damnation?</hi> Conſider that, <hi>Mat. 10. 14, 15. Whoſoever ſhall not receive you, and heare your words, ſhake off the duſt of your feete; It ſhall be eaſier for Sodom and Gomorrah in the day of Judgement then for that Citie.</hi> Why ſo? See the reaſon, <hi>ver. 40. He that receives you, receives me,</hi> and ſo alſo, he that refuſes you refuſes me. So then, he that refuſed to receive the Apoſtles, their ſinne was that they refuſed to receive Chriſt. And what ſhould become of thoſe that refuſed to receive him? Gods vengeance ſhall lie heavier upon ſuch mens heads at the day of Judgement, then upon the head of a curſed damned Sodomite. That ſin ſhall preſſe and ſinke a mans ſoule deeper into hell then <hi>Sodoms</hi> ſin. How heavie and dreadfull will <hi>Sodoms</hi> Hell be in Hell, whoſe ſinne made a viſible Hell on earth? and ſuch an Hell on earth, the monuments whereof remaine ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, and exemplary to this day, to be a terrour to all ungodly ones. And yet
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:153914:24"/> as heavy as <hi>Sodoms</hi> puniſhment ſhall be, it ſhall be eaſier then thine, that recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt not Chriſt when offered unto thee. Indeed when Chriſt would have come into a village of <hi>Samaria,</hi> Luk. 9. 53. they would not receive him, <hi>and they did not receive him,</hi> ſayes the Text. The Diſciples would have had fire from heaven to have conſumed them. And if they thought they were worthy of fire from heaven, that would not receive him but to lodge in their Towne, and in ſome of their houſes; How much more ſhall they be judged worthy of fire in hell, that doe not, and will not receive him into their hearts, when his Miniſters offer him to men, and labour to make ready for him? And though then Chriſt would not have fire come downe upon thoſe <hi>Samaritans,</hi> yet when the time of judgement comes, he will bring fiery vengeance upon all thoſe that have not received him into their hearts, 2 <hi>Theſ. 1. 7, 8. When the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſhall be revealed from heaven in flaming fire, taking vengeance on them that know not God, and that obey not the Goſpel of our
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:153914:25"/> Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Not to obey the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, is not to obey the commandements of the Goſpel, as not to obey the Law, is not to obey the commandements of the Law. Now the maine commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Goſpel is, <hi>Receive the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> This commandement not obeyed, will bring fiery vengeance on his head that obeyes it not. Oh that men would but thinke ſeriouſly of this danger. The ſtouteſt, ſturdieſt, and moſt rebellious ſpirit that ever was, when he ſhall ſee Chriſt come in Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſhall then with howling and wring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of hands cry out upon himſelf, Ah curſed wretch that I am, oh that I had had the grace to have received this Lord Chriſt, when he was offered to me! Ah beaſt and foole, that I received him not when I was ſo often preſſed to it, now ſhall I receive vengeance, and wrath for ever, becauſe I received not the Lord Chriſt! Nay thinke upon one thing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo before that day come. There will be a day of Death before the day of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Thou muſt dye, and thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt not how ſoone, and when thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:153914:25"/> to dye, like enough thou wilt take up <hi>Stephens</hi> prayer, <hi>Acts 7. 59. Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus receive my ſpirit.</hi> Then full faine wilt thou be to have <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> receive thy ſoule. Now wouldeſt thou in good ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt have Chriſt Jeſus receive thy ſoule when thou dyeſt? why then, be as wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to receive Chriſt Jeſus into thy ſoule whileſt thou liveſt. He will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive no ſoule that hath not firſt recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him. In vaine ſhalt thou cry at thy laſt gaſpe; Lord Jeſus receive my ſoule, if thy ſoule have not before received him. He will returne thee a cold and a comfortleſſe anſwer, Oh now yee can call to mee to receive your ſoule, I cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led all the dayes of your life to receive me, for theſe thirty, forty, fifty yeares together, and you would never bee brought to receive me. As you have dealt by me, ſo will I now deale by you. I will now be quit with you, I called upon you to receive me, and yee would not, now cry you on, and howle on to me, to receive you, I will as little regard your calles, as you regarded mine: your owne meaſure be mete unto you. Let
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:153914:26"/> this meditation ſinke deeply downe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our hearts, and as willingly as wee would have Chriſt receive our ſoules at death, and as willingly as wee would be received into everlaſting habitations at the laſt day, ſo willingly, ſo gladly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Lord Jeſus Chriſt now he is offered to you in the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>It being a matter of ſo great conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence and neceſſitie to receive Chriſt, <note place="margin">Queſt.</note> how may wee come, and what muſt be done to receive him?</p>
               <p>They that will receive Chriſt, there muſt be two things done by them. <note place="margin">Anſw.</note>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. All hindrances muſt be removed.</item>
                  <item>2. Some poſitive duties muſt be done.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hindrances</hi> to be removed by ſuch as will receive Chriſt.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>FIrſt,</hi> All ſuch things muſt be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that hinder the ſoule from Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving Chriſt. There is no man that receives not Chriſt, but there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that holds him off. We reade of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:153914:26"/> a man in the Goſpel that had a <hi>withered arme.</hi> Now if a man would have offered him money upon condition that hee would have received it with his hand, he could not have received it, becauſe his arme was withered. So God offers Chriſt to be received, and men receive him not, becauſe their armes are withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. A Palſey ſhaking hand may receive an almes, but a withered hand cannot. Now there is one thing or other that withers the hand of the ſoule, that it cannot ſtretch out it ſelfe to receive Chriſt. Men muſt therefore firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, what that is which withers their hand &amp; arme, and muſt get that firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, before they can receive Chriſt. When Antichriſt was to come into the world, he could not be received <hi>untill that which hindred were taken out of the way,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2. 7. when Chriſt would and ſhould be received, there is ſtill ſome one thing or other, that lets and hinders it. And he cannot be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, till that which hinders be taken out of the way. Let us ſee what thoſe hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drances are, that muſt be firſt taken out
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:153914:27"/> of the way. They are theſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> An over-good conceit of a <note place="margin">1.</note> mans own condition and eſtate, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he is for the preſent. Such a conceit diſconceits a man of the neceſſitie of Chriſt, and makes him regardleſſe of him when offered. Offer to a man a thing that he needs not, and he will not be at the paines to reach forth his hand to receive it. What cares he to receive a thing he needs not? Offer an almes to a rich man, and he ſcornes it, what he take an almes, that hath money of his owne in his purſe? he thinkes it an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe, a diſgrace, and a diſparagement to him for one of his ranke and repute, to have an almes offered him. But offer it to a poore man, to a needy perſon, his heart is gladded at the offer, and hee thankfully receives it. A man that thinkes highly well of his eſtate alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, he thinkes meanly of Chriſt. <hi>The whole need not the Phyſitian,</hi> need no Phyſicke, and therefore care neither for Phyſicke, nor Phyſitian. Men that are ſtrongly poſſeſt with the conceit of the preſent goodneſſe of their eſtates,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:153914:27"/> and conditions, Chriſt is vile in their eyes. A man therefore that would ever receive Chriſt, muſt firſt emptie his heart of all ſuch conceits, and be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſence and under the pinch too of ſelfe-emptineſſe. A man that would receive Chriſt, muſt come with an emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hand. The full ſtomack deſpiſes the honey-combs of the Goſpel, and the full hand will never receive Chriſt offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Stout-hearted perſons are farre from righteouſneſſe, <hi>Iſa. 46. 12. Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken unto mee yee ſtout-hearted, that are far from righteouſneſſe, I bring neere my righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe.</hi> God brings Chriſt, and his righteouſneſſe neere to men, he offers it them in the miniſtry of the Goſpel, and yet though it be brought neere, they are farre from it, becauſe they doe not receive it. And why doe they not receive it, when it is brought ſo neere unto them? Becauſe they <hi>are ſtout-hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi> They have a conceit, that their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate is good already, and they build and reſt upon a righteouſneſſe of their own in their moralities and performances; and this conceit makes them ſo <hi>ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:153914:28"/> that they will not ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the righteouſneſſe of God,</hi> Rom. 10. 3. <hi>Wee are Lords, wee will not come unto thee,</hi> Jer. 2. 31. Beggers will come and receive Gods offers, and his almes, but whileſt men conceit themſelves to be Lords, to have Lords eſtates, they will neither come, nor receive Gods offers. If therefore wee would receive Chriſt, wee muſt away with all theſe ſwelling conceits, wee muſt away with our <hi>Lordſhips,</hi> with our <hi>ſtoutneſſe,</hi> and fulneſſe, and labour to ſee our curſed and damnable condition by nature, the emptineſſe and vanitie of all wee have, and doe, we muſt be in a <hi>periſhing</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, <hi>Luk.</hi> 15. 17. in a <hi>loſt</hi> condition, <hi>Luk.</hi> 19. 10. He that will be Chriſts diſciple, and receive him for his Lord, muſt deny himſelfe. The Apoſtle, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. counts all things dung, that he may winne and receive Chriſt. And Chriſt before he offers <hi>Laodicea</hi> Gold, Ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and eye-ſalve, he firſt convinces her of her poverty, beggery, nakedneſſe, and labours, to empty her of her ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>love, and ſelfe-conceitedneſſe that ſhee
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:153914:28"/> was rich, and needed nothing. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by giving to underſtand, that it is a moſt dangerous hindrance that keepes men from receiving Chriſt, to have an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>good conceit of a mans owne naturall eſtate, of what he hath, and doth. As e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver therefore thou wilt receive Chriſt, away with it. <hi>Such as goe downe to the duſt,</hi> and in the ſence of their wretched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe are laid in the duſt; <hi>That cannot keepe alive their owne ſoules,</hi> and ſee no way but death, they they are, that will <hi>bow</hi> to Chriſt, and receive him with all their ſoules, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22. 29.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The <hi>love of our luſts,</hi> a hindrance from receiving Chriſt.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>ANother maine hindrance to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is a love of our luſts, an inordinate love of our profits, pleaſures, credits, &amp;c. Our luſts loved at all, our profits and pleaſures over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, doe altogether hinder a man from receiving of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> A mans luſts
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:153914:29"/> muſt be caſt out, if <hi>Chriſt</hi> be received in. Now mens luſts are deare to them, men are ſtrongly bewitcht with them, and they will never endure to receive <hi>Chriſt</hi> upon ſuch termes, as to turne their luſts going. When <hi>Chriſt</hi> is once received for the husband, there muſt be a bill of Divorce given to all theſe, and they muſt be packt out. That's death to a carnall heart to doe ſo, he can as eaſily die as doe it, and therefore will rather refuſe to receive <hi>Chriſt,</hi> then he will receive him upon ſuch harſh termes. When it was propounded to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Emperour to receive <hi>Chriſt</hi> for a God, the Senate refuſed to doe it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they underſtood if he were recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved as a God, he onely muſt be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and no other with him, all other gods muſt downe, if they received him: upon the very ſame ground it is that men doe not receive <hi>Chriſt</hi> into their hearts; becauſe they ſee that if <hi>Chriſt</hi> be received, their luſts muſt out of doores, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> alone muſt have their hearts. <hi>Chriſt</hi> will not be received by us whileſt the roomes of our hearts are
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:153914:29"/> taken up by baſe and ſinfull luſts. As when he was borne, he was faine to be in the ſtable, <hi>becauſe no roome for him in the Inne,</hi> Luk. 2. 7. So if we make, and will have our hearts common Innes, and receptacles for luſts to harbour and lodge them, <hi>How long ſhall thy vaine thoughts lodge within thee?</hi> Jer. 4. 14. Chriſt cannot, will not be received, becauſe there is no <hi>Roome</hi> for him. What was the reaſon <hi>Diatrephes</hi> would not receive <hi>John,</hi> but <hi>becauſe he loved to have the preheminence?</hi> 3 John 9. Luſts love to have the preheminence in the heart, and therefore keepe out Chriſt from being received, becauſe if he be received, they muſt loſe their prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence, and they had as lieve loſe their lives as that. So it is alſo in the inordinate love of the world, and our profits. It was a faire offer which was made to them, <hi>Luk. 14. Come; for all things are ready:</hi> Receive Chriſt tendred to you in the Goſpel, and yee ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive with him all things your ſoules can deſire. And yet they received not Chriſt in that offer, and all becauſe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:153914:30"/> their oxen, and their farmes inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately loved, drew their hearts ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way. It is ſo in the caſe of credit and reſpect in the world, inordinately reſpected. Chriſt is offered to many a man in the world, but he ſtickes at re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving him. What is the matter? Oh, ſayes he, If I receive him, I ſhall receive but little credit by it in the world, nay, I ſhall loſe credit and reſpect amongſt my friends. If I might receive Chriſt, and credit both, I could then receive him; but becauſe if Chriſt be received my credit will be gone, therefore I will none, I will not meddle. Our Saviour charging thoſe with this ſinne of not receiving him, <hi>Joh. 5. 43. I am come in my Fathers name, and yee receive mee not,</hi> doth there ſhew this very thing to be the reaſon of their not receiving him, <hi>ver. 44. How can yee beleeve which receive honour one of another?</hi> As if he had ſaid, I complaine that yee receive mee not; and indeed it is no wonder yee receive me not, when yee receive honour one of another, that is, you deſire to have credit, reſpect, eſteeme, and good opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:153914:30"/> one of another. You ſee if any one receive me, all his fellows will hate him, ſcorne, ſleight, and diſ-eſteeme him, and you ſtand ſo much upon your honour and credit, one amongſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that it is impoſſible for you thus inordinately affected to your credit, ever to receive me. So that if ever wee would receive Chriſt, we muſt caſheire all our luſts, ſend them packing. Wee muſt renounce all our carnall luſts, worldly luſts, and ſee more gaine to be received in receiving Chriſt, then in all the Oxen and Farmes in the world. Be willing to ſacrifice thy credit and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme in the world, and be content to be the reproach of the world, ſo thou mayeſt but receive, and enjoy him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Falſe and groundleſſe feares, <hi>a hindrance to the receiving of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THere be many that goe further then in the former caſes, that doe haply <note place="margin">3.</note> ſeriouſly deſire to receive Chriſt, and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:153914:31"/> yet dare not, but are afraid to doe it. Not afraid, becauſe of parting with their luſts, with their profits, credit, eaſe, &amp;c. but afraid in regard of their owne unworthineſſe. They feare that it will be over-boldly, and ſaucily done, for ſuch as they are to offer to receive Chriſt, in that guilty and unworthy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition in which they ſtand. They have been foule and filthy ſinners; what have they to doe to receive Chriſt, or to meddle with him? Surely Chriſt will never be received by ſuch hainous ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners as they are. Theſe falſe feares keepe many a ſoule from that forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in receiving Chriſt that ſhould be. But theſe be feares for which no ground at all: for <hi>firſt;</hi> God offers him to ſuch ſinners, and calls upon ſuch ſinners to receive him. He was offered to, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by thoſe very men that crucified him, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. It is not humilitie to ſtand ſtraining courteſie, when God offers Chriſt. Nay, God offering Chriſt to ſuch ſinners, it is diſobedience, and not humilitie, not to receive him. It is no preſumption, no boldneſſe, no ſauci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:153914:31"/> to do that which God commands us to doe. It is a faithleſſe feare, and a falſe humility to hang backe when God wills us to receive him. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Chriſt received ſinners, <hi>Luk.</hi> 15. 2. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hainous ſinners may receive <hi>Chriſt. Zacheus</hi> a Publican, and ſuch a ſinner, as the people murmure at Chriſt for his ſake, <hi>Luk.</hi> 19. 7. and yet Chriſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered himſelfe to be received, and was received by him. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> If thou be ſo unworthy, and ſo great a ſinner, the more need thou haſt to receive him. The greater thine unworthineſſe, the greater need of Chriſt to take off thine unworthineſſe. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> If none ſhould receive Chriſt till they were worthy, who ſhould ever have him? <hi>Fiftly,</hi> who ever was refuſed for his unworthineſſe that had a deſire to receive him? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what ever thy ſinnes, and unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe be, I ſay unto thee as the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel ſaid to <hi>Joſeph</hi> whileſt he was in that demur what to doe, <hi>Mat. 1. 20. Feare not,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>to take Mary thy wife; to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive her for thy wife.</hi> So I ſay, what ever thy ſinnes have been, what ever thine
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:153914:32"/> owne unworthineſſe be, feare not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Chriſt Jeſus thine husband. It is an undervaluing of Chriſt, when wee feare in this caſe to receive him; as if his worthineſſe were not ſuch as could ſwallow up all our unworthineſſe. It is ſtrange to ſee Satans fetches. It is his plot with moſt men to keep them from receiving Chriſt by a conceit of their worthineſſe, and when he ſees that men once come to ſee their unworthineſſe, and their need of Chriſt, and a deſire to receive him, then he ſtaves them of with their unworthineſſe, and would have them ſo over-mannerly, as not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him, becauſe of their unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Shall a poore, meane conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned woman refuſe the offer of a rich husband, becauſe ſhee is poore and beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly, or hath ſhee not the more reaſon to accept it for her poverty? In ſuch a caſe it were a fond thing to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humble, as to ſtand in her owne light, and hinder her ſelfe for ever. When <hi>David</hi> made the tender of marriage to <hi>Abagail,</hi> ſhee in her humility of ſpirit confeſſes her ſelfe not worthy of ſuch
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:153914:32"/> a match, <hi>Let thine handmaid be a ſervant to waſh the feet of the ſervants of my Lord, 1 Sam.</hi> 25. 41. But yet for all that, ſhee refuſes not the offer, but <hi>ſhee aroſe, and made haſt, and followed after the meſſengers of David, and became his wife,</hi> verſe 42. So when Chriſt offers himſelfe to be received as our Husband, let us not ſtand ſo much in our owne light, as to refuſe to receive him, becauſe of our unworthineſſe of ſuch a favour. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe wee our unworthineſſe of it, but yet <hi>riſe up,</hi> and <hi>make haſt,</hi> and follow af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the meſſengers of Chriſt, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his wife. Why ſhould wee ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at that, at which Chriſt ſtumbled not? If any ſhould ſtumble at unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe, it ſhould be Chriſt himſelfe. And when he notwithſtanding our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe offers himſelfe; why ſhould not wee receive his offer? If our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe be no barre to his offer, why ſhould it be to our receiving? If <hi>David</hi> thinke not unworthily of <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gail,</hi> but is content and deſirous to make her his wife, why then ſhould <hi>Abigail</hi> under a pretence of unworthineſſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:153914:33"/> to receive <hi>David</hi> for her husband?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The <hi>Poſitive Duty</hi> which muſt be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of all that will receive Chriſt.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe ſecond thing</hi> is the Poſitive Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <note place="margin">2.</note> to be done for the receiving of Chriſt. And the duty to be done is, <hi>To beleeve.</hi> To beleeve, is to receive Chriſt, and when wee doe beleeve, wee doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him, <hi>Joh. 1. 12. To as many</hi> as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him, <hi>that is, to as many as beleeved in his name.</hi> So <hi>Joh. 5. 43, 44. Yee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive me not, how can yee beleeve?</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they received him not, becauſe they beleeved not. Then Chriſt is received when he dwells in our hearts, and he dwells in our hearts by faith, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3. 17. For the better underſtanding of this point, wee muſt know, that the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of Chriſt by faith, ſtands in ſetting faith on work in the ſeverall acts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Now, faith is to be conſidered as the <hi>eye</hi> of the ſoule, and as <hi>the hand</hi> of the ſoule, and in receiving of Chriſt,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:153914:33"/> it muſt be ſet on worke as both. There be falſe faiths in the world. Some faith is <hi>all eye,</hi> and <hi>no hand,</hi> it ſees and knowes not, it applyes, and apprehends nothing. Some faith is <hi>all hand,</hi> will be catching, and ſnatching at Chriſt, it is <hi>no eye.</hi> The firſt is a <hi>lame faith,</hi> the ſecond is a <hi>blind faith.</hi> 2 Sam. 5. 8. <hi>The blind, and the lame were hated of Davids ſoule,</hi> ſo is the Idoll faith, the lame and blinde faith of the world hated of Gods ſoule; and as it is there ſaid; <hi>The blinde, and the lame ſhall not come into the houſe,</hi> ſo neither ſhall they come into heaven, becauſe neither a lame nor a blinde faith doe receive Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> then the faith that will receive <note place="margin">1.</note> Chriſt, muſt be ſet on worke as <hi>the eye</hi> of the ſoule. A man that will receive Chriſt, muſt firſt ſee Chriſt, ſee his worth, excellency, beauty, and all-ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency. He muſt ſo ſee him, that he may ſee him worth the receiving, worth the having. A man will never care to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that, or once put out his hand to take that, in which he ſees no worth. But when a man ſees a thing offered
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:153914:34"/> wherein he ſees worth, the worth of it will make him reach out to receive it. <hi>Zacheus</hi> did receive Chriſt into his houſe, and into his heart, but the firſt ſtep to it was <hi>a deſire to ſee him,</hi> and he firſt gat up into the Sycamore tree <hi>to ſee him.</hi> The word, and the miniſtry of the Goſpel is the Sycamore tree, by ſtudious reading, and hearing the word, muſt men get up into the Sycamore, from whence they may ſee Chriſt. It is in this caſe as in <hi>Eves</hi> tentation. The Divell offers her the forbidden fruit, and ſhee receives it; ſhee ſhould not have received it, but ſee what moved her to receive it. <hi>Gen. 3. 6. And when</hi> ſhee ſaw <hi>that the tree was good for foode, that it was a</hi> deſire to the eyes, <hi>and a tree to be deſired to make one wiſe, ſhee tooke of the fruit,</hi> ſhee received it: ſhee lookt through falſe glaſſes, and was gulled with falſe apprehenſions, but yet thus much wee may ſee by it; that when wee ſee, and judge a thing offered to be of worth, precious, and deſireable, that that is the next way to make it receive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. And thus is it in receiving Chriſt.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:153914:34"/> 
                  <hi>As the Apple-tree among the trees of the wood, ſo is my beloved amongst the ſonnes; I ſate downe under his ſhadow with great delight, and his fruit was ſweet unto my taſt,</hi> Cant. 2. 3. If ever wee would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the fruit of this tree, wee muſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour by the eye of faith to ſee the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of this tree, and the fruit of it. Wee muſt firſt ſee that Chriſt as farre excells all other things, as the Apple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree doth excell all the ordinary and common trees of the wood, that there is delight under his ſhadow, that there is ſweetneſſe in his fruit, that it is a tree good for foode, that it is a deſire to the eyes, that it is a tree to be deſired to make one wiſe indeed, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 30. He of God is made unto us wiſdome. And the excellencies of this tree once ſeene, would holily tempt us to receive the offered fruits thereof. We ſee <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 11, 12. that the Diſciples, and the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full received Chriſt, when others re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him not, <hi>His owne received him not,</hi> yet wee his Diſciples received him. But how came they to receive him? They did it by faith, <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. But marke
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:153914:35"/> what was the firſt act of faith in recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him; That wee ſee <hi>verſ. 14. And we</hi> beheld his glory, <hi>the glory as of the onely begotten of the Father.</hi> Our faith pierced through the vaile, and covert of the fleſh. <hi>We ſaw him,</hi> and prized him as the onely begotten Sonne of God, and ſo by the eye of faith ſeeing the glory and excellency of Chriſt, wee received him. Looke how <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes in the caſe of Receiving <hi>Epaphroditus,</hi> Phil. 2. 29. <hi>Receive him therefore in the Lord, with all gladneſſe, and hold ſuch in reputation. Paul</hi> would have him be received, and received gladly, and therefore that they might the readilier doe that, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es them to have him in Reputation. Hee knew well enough, that if they did not prize him, if they had eſteemed him a fellow of little worth, that had nothing in him, that they would never receive him, at leaſt with no gladneſſe. But if they did but conſider that he was a man of worth, that he was a precious man, and ſo had him in reputation according to his deſert, that they would receive him with all gladneſſe. So is it in the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:153914:35"/> receiving of Chriſt. Hold him once in reputation, and wee ſhall receive him with all gladneſſe. Labour by the eye of faith to ſee his precious excellencies, and wee cannot but hold him in Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
               <p>Faith firſt ſhewes to the ſoule the precious excellencies, and glories of Chriſt, it repreſents him exceeding precious to the ſoule, as the eye it lets in the excellency of Chriſt into the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding upon which the affections are raiſed, and ſtirred up to the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of him. Wee ſhall ſee it made good in two Texts. One is that, <hi>Mat. 13. 45, 46. The Kingdome of heaven is like unto a Merchant man ſeeking goodly pearles, who when he hath found one pearle of great price, he went and ſold all that he had, and bought it.</hi> He ſells all you ſee to receive that pearle, what moves him to it? Hee found one pearle of <hi>great price.</hi> Here is then the firſt thing that ſets all the reſt on worke, he ſaw it was a pearle of price, of great price, of great worth, he ſaw it was worth the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, worth the having. He that ever
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:153914:36"/> will receive this bleſſed pearle that is offered in the Goſpel, muſt firſt have the eye of faith to ſee the price, value, and worth of it. Another place is that, <hi>Cant. 6. 1. Whither is thy beloved gone? whither is thy beloved turned aſide, that wee may ſeeke him with thee?</hi> as if they had ſaid, wee have a great deſire to receive Chriſt. But how was this deſire raiſed? That wee may ſee, <hi>Chap. 5. verſ. 9, 10.</hi> and ſo to the end. The Church had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of her beloved, of her Chriſt, <hi>ver.</hi> 8. Thereupon others aske her what this beloved is, and this Chriſt is, with whom ſhee makes ſo much adoe. Shee therefore deſcribes and ſets him forth in all his excellencies, beauties, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; and tells them, <hi>ver. 16. That he is altogether lovely, altogether deſires,</hi> or <hi>wholly deſirable things.</hi> Now when upon this deſcription and relation of hers, they ſee the invaluable worth, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of Chriſt, when they ſee him to be wholly deſires, then are their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires wholly to receive him; Then they cry out, <hi>Whither is thy beloved gone, that wee may ſeeke him with thee?</hi> So that the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:153914:36"/> eye of faith is the firſt in-let of Chriſt into the ſoule, and this act of faith in ſeeing Chriſts excellencies, is the firſt in receiving Chriſt. And therefore when the Apoſtle gives us the ſum of the Goſpel, Chriſt crucified for ſinnes, marke how he ſpeakes, 1 <hi>Tim. 1. 15. This is a faithfull ſaying,</hi> and ſayes not which ought to bee received of all. That's true, this Chriſt and this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine concerning him, is to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: But he addes withall, a ſecret ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to perſwade men to receive it. <hi>It is worthy to be received of all.</hi> Thereby ſhewing that before men will receive the Goſpel, and receive Chriſt, they muſt ſee Chriſt to be worthy of all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation, and that when they ſee Chriſt worthy of all acceptation, then they will ſet upon the receiving of him. This is then the firſt thing in receiving Chriſt, an high prizing of him, and his excellencies, which makes way to the actual! receiving of him; For the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding being throughly and truly convinced of his excellencies, the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions neceſſarily follow, and ſtirre up
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:153914:37"/> proportionable endeavours for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of him. And what is the cauſe that men doe not receive Chriſt, but the ignorance of his worth? <hi>Joh. 4. 10. If thou kneweſt the gift of God, and who it is that ſayes to thee, Give mee to drinke, thou wouldeſt have asked of him.</hi> Rom. 10. 3. <hi>For they being ignorant of Gods righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, have not ſubmitted themſelves unto the righteouſneſſe of God.</hi> Mens ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of Chriſt, breeds in them a low prizing, and a baſe undervaluing of him, and therefore every vile thing is prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before him. It was a vile ſin which is complained of, <hi>Amos 2. 6. That they ſold the righteous for ſilver, and the poore for a paire of ſhooes.</hi> A vile ſinne that <hi>Joel</hi> complaines of, <hi>Joel 3. 3. They have cast lots upon my people, and have given a boy for an harlot, and ſold a girle for wine, that they might drinke.</hi> It was a vile ſinne in <hi>Judas,</hi> that he ſold, and prized Chriſt at thirty pieces: <hi>A goodly price that I was prized at of them.</hi> Zech. 11. 13. It was the price at which ſlaves were prized. <hi>Exod.</hi> 21. 32. Now if ſo baſe a thing in the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> to prize the righteous
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:153914:37"/> and the poore ſo baſely, as to ſell them for old ſhooes, to ſell a boy for an har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot, if in <hi>Judas</hi> to prize Chriſt but at thirty pieces, what is it then to prize Chriſt under old ſhooes, to ſell him for an harlot, for wine, for uncleane and drunken luſts? And yet thus is Chriſt prized by men, men will ſell him for old ſhooes, for an harlot, for a pot, for a penny. So baſely is the precious Lord of Glory viliprized by ſinfull men. And becauſe men ſo wofully un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervalue him, and eſteeme ſo baſely of him, therefore it is they receive him not; for who would trouble himſelfe to be at that paines that is required in the receiving of Chriſt, that doth not prize him above thirty pieces, above an harlot, above wine, above old ſhooes? Now, as this baſe under-prizing of Chriſt makes men neglect the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of him, ſo certainly when men once have the eye of faith to ſee the due worth, and the true excellencies of Chriſt, then will they beſtirre them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for the receiving of him. See <hi>Mat. 14. 35, 36. And when the men of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:153914:38"/> the place</hi> had knowledge of him, <hi>they ſent out into all the Countrey round about, and brought unto him all that were diſeaſed, and beſought him that they might onely touch the hem of his garment.</hi> So, had men now but the knowledge of Chriſt, and knew how rich, how precious a Chriſt he were, they would flocke thicke and threefold after him, and be earneſt ſutors that they might receive him. It is Chriſts preciouſneſſe well viewed by faith that fetches men in unto him. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 4. As therefore wee would frame our ſoules to the receiving of Chriſt, ſo ſtudy Chriſt, ſtudy his excellencies, view his beauties. It is a noble ſtudy to ſtudy Chriſt: The Angels in Heaven are ſtudents in this Divinity, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to looke into, to pry into theſe things. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 12. It is the ſame word that is uſed of <hi>Johns</hi> looking into <hi>Chriſts</hi> grave, <hi>Joh. 20. 5. And he ſtooped downe and looked in,</hi> becauſe he would through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee how things were, hee ſtooped downe to looke wiſhly and narrowly; with ſuch earneſtneſſe, with ſuch deſire looke the bleſſed Angels into the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:153914:38"/> of the Goſpel, they ſtoop down, and look into them. They do not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtudy, but wondrous hard doe they ſtudy the unſearchable riches of Chriſt; If the Angels have benefit by Chriſt, yet what is their benefit to ours? Chriſt came for us, was Incarnate, and cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied for us, how much more concernes it us to looke into theſe things then the Angels? The looking into the Arke coſt them full deare, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6. 19. It is our undoing that now wee doe not look into the Arke. It was death for the <hi>Ko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hathites</hi> that were Levites to look into the Sanctuary, and ſee the holy things. <hi>Numb.</hi> 4. 4. 20. But now it is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, God now under the Goſpel hath unveyled all the holy things, and the very Arke which was in the holy of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, is to be ſeene, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 11. 19. It is our ſin, and it is our death not to pry now into the Arke. 2 <hi>Cor. 4. 3. If our Goſpel be hid, it is hid to them that periſh.</hi> Pry therefore into the Arke, and there ſee the treaſures of all grace, and good laid up, ſo fixe thine eye upon theſe treaſures, as thou mayeſt be ſtirred up
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:153914:39"/> to an holy covetouſneſſe, and greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of receiving them.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The faith that will receive Chriſt, muſt worke as <hi>an hand:</hi> And it <note place="margin">2.</note> muſt doe a double worke of the hand.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Faith muſt <hi>ſtretch</hi> out it ſelfe <note place="margin">1.</note> and <hi>reach</hi> out it ſelfe to receive Chriſt. If a man would receive Chriſt, he muſt doe in this caſe, as Chriſt ſpake to him <hi>Mark.</hi> 3. 5. <hi>Stretch forth thine hand.</hi> This ſtretching forth of the hand, is up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſight of Chriſts excellencies, to ſtirre up in our hearts, ſtrong, vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, reſtleſſe, and affectionate deſires after him. <hi>Cant.</hi> 8. 2. <hi>Oh that thou wert as my brother, that ſucked the breaſts of my mother!</hi> Oh that I had this precious Lord Chriſt! oh that he were mine, that I were poſſeſſed of him! This is the <hi>Lifting up of the doores and gates, Pſal.</hi> 24. 7. When the ſoule is lifted, and raiſed up after Chriſt in ſtrong de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to enjoy him; theſe deſires are the reaching, and ſtretching forth of the hand to receive him. And ſuch a reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the hand of the ſoule, ſhall not miſſe of receiving Chriſt. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:153914:39"/> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed are they that hunger and thirſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Righteouſneſſe, for they ſhall be filled.</hi> Therefore they ſhall receive, or elſe how be filled? It is as if he had ſaid; Bleſſed are they that ſtretch out their hands, for they ſhall receive. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 22. 17. <hi>Let him that is athirſt come, and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever will let him take the water of life freely.</hi> Thirſt will make a man reach and ſtretch forth the hand for water, and <hi>reaching</hi> helpes to <hi>receiving.</hi> The Law of God was, <hi>Deut.</hi> 24. 15. that a poore man ſhould receive his pay at his day: and ſee what is one reaſon for it. <hi>Becauſe he lifts up his ſoule unto it;</hi> that is, he ſets his heart upon it, with a ſtrong deſire to receive it, and therefore God would not have him diſappointed. Now ſurely God will not deale worſe with a poore ſoule, then he would have them deale with a poore man. If a poore man that hath lifted up his ſoule in deſires after his hyre, muſt not be diſappointed, but muſt receive his hyre, then ſurely when GOD ſees a poore ſoule lift up it ſelfe, and reaching out it ſelfe in its deſires after Chriſt, he will
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:153914:40"/> not have it diſappointed of receiving Chriſt. What compariſon betweene wages deſired, and Chriſt deſired? The LORD that will not in his goodneſſe have the deſires of poore men, will much leſſe ſuffer the deſires of poore ſoules after Chriſt be deceived.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Faith as the hand, muſt <hi>lay hold</hi> upon, take, claſpe about, and faſten <note place="margin">2.</note> upon Chriſt offered. Wee ſee <hi>Luk.</hi> 2. 26. that <hi>Simeon</hi> had it revealed unto him that he ſhould ſee the Lords Chriſt. And when Chriſt was brought into the Temple by his parents, he doth view him, and looks upon him; but yet that would not ſatisfie him, to ſee him; but <hi>verſ.</hi> 28. <hi>Then he took him up in his armes.</hi> Faith doth as <hi>Simeon</hi> did, It not onely viewes, and ſees Chriſt, and his worth, but ſeeing him it reaches out after him, and takes him up in his Armes, claſpes about him, and holds him faſt for her owne. And hence is the phraſe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving Chriſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 12. And <hi>Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the promiſes, 1. Tim.</hi> 1. 15. And the phraſe of <hi>embracing the promiſes, Heb.</hi> 11. 13. And <hi>laying hold on eternall life,</hi>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:153914:40"/> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 12. And this act of faith in receiving Chriſt, is that, <hi>Cant.</hi> 8. 2. <hi>I would lead thee, and bring thee into thy mothers houſe.</hi> When God offers Chriſt in the Goſpel a Lord, and a Saviour, and wee take Chriſt for our Lord, and Saviour, then doe wee receive him. Behold, ſayes God, I offer you Chriſt to be your Lord and Saviour; Now then comes faith and hath a double act.</p>
               <p>An Act of the underſtanding, by <note place="margin">1.</note> which as the eye of the ſoule it ſees as the neceſſity, ſo the worth, and price of Chriſt. Here, ſayes faith, I ſee a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry precious Chriſt, I ſee wonderfull worth, and excellency in him, I ſee he is well worth the looking after, well worth the having, and receiving.</p>
               <p>An Act of the will. And that is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold; <note place="margin">2.</note> 
                  <hi>firſt,</hi> as the hand of the ſoule to <hi>reach</hi> and <hi>ſtretch</hi> out it ſelfe after Chriſt in vehement and ſtrong deſires after him. Here faith ſayes, oh that I had this precious Chriſt, oh that this precious Chriſt were mine! oh that upon any termes my Soule might enjoy him!
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:153914:41"/> 
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> as the hand of the ſoule to <hi>lay hold</hi> upon, to apply, and take Chriſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered. Here faith ſayes, This precious Chriſt I doe willingly and gladly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, I lay hold upon him as my Lord, and Saviour. Behold Lord, as thou of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereſt him unto me, ſo doe I receive, and take him, <hi>My Lord, and my God;</hi> Welcome Lord Chriſt, I claſpe about thee with both mine armes. And thus by theſe two Acts of faith is Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into the heart.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>to know,</hi> whether wee have received Chriſt already.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>IF Chriſt muſt be received, then try wee, and examine wee our ſelves whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wee have received him or no. It concernes every man to examine him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe whether he be a true Chriſtian or not. No man is a true Chriſtian till Chriſt be received, therefore as it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes us to try whether wee be true Chriſtians or not, ſo it concernes us to
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:153914:41"/> try whether wee have received Chriſt or not.</p>
               <p>How may it be knowne whether <note place="margin">Queſt.</note> Chriſt be received or not?</p>
               <p>It may be knowne by divers things. <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> Try it by theſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> By this in the Text. <hi>As ye have</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1.</note> 
                  <hi>received Chriſt Jeſus the Lord.</hi> Mark then what they do that truly receive Chriſt. They that truly receive Chriſt, receive him not onely a <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> but they receive him alſo a <hi>Lord Jeſus,</hi> a Chriſt the Lord. They receive him not onely a <hi>Saving,</hi> but a <hi>Ruling</hi> Chriſt. They that receive Chriſt indeed, receive him as God offers him in the Word, now he offers him an whole Chriſt to <hi>ſave</hi> and <hi>rule</hi> both, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 5. <hi>Wee preach Chriſt Jeſus the Lord,</hi> we preach, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him to you a Chriſt Jeſus, a <hi>Saving Chriſt,</hi> a Chriſt to <hi>ſave,</hi> and wee preach, and offer him to you Chriſt the <hi>Lord,</hi> a <hi>Ruling Chriſt,</hi> a Chriſt to <hi>Rule.</hi> Chriſt is called the <hi>Lords Chriſt.</hi> Luk. 2. 26. <hi>Till he had ſeene the Lords Chriſt.</hi> Our Saviour tells us, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. 24. <hi>That there ſhall ariſe falſe Chriſts.</hi> And the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:153914:42"/> world is full of falſe Chriſts, Idoll Chriſts, Chriſts bred in the braines of ignorant heads. Now a mans care ſhould be to receive a true Chriſt, the Lords Chriſt. But how ſhould one know the Lords Chriſt from the falſe and Idoll Chriſts of the world? What a kinde of Chriſt is the Lords Chriſt? See <hi>Zech.</hi> 6. 13. <hi>A Prieſt upon his throne.</hi> That is expounded by two places. <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 36. <hi>God hath made Jeſus both Lord, and Chriſt.</hi> Acts 5. 31. <hi>He hath exalted him to be a</hi> Prince <hi>and</hi> a Saviour, <hi>to give re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and forgiveneſſe of ſinnes.</hi> A <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> to give forgiveneſſe, and a <hi>Prince</hi> to give repentance; A <hi>Saviour</hi> to give <hi>pardon</hi> of, and a <hi>Prince</hi> to give <hi>Power</hi> againſt ſinne. So then, <hi>the Lords Chriſt</hi> which he offers is <hi>the Lord Chriſt,</hi> not onely a <hi>Saving,</hi> but a <hi>Ruling,</hi> not onely a <hi>pardoning,</hi> but a <hi>reforming</hi> Chriſt, not onely a Chriſt with a <hi>ſacrifice,</hi> but a Chriſt with a <hi>Scepter,</hi> and a <hi>Crowne,</hi> not onely a Chriſt with <hi>bloud,</hi> but a Chriſt with <hi>water.</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. Now then if wee have received Chriſt, wee have received him ſuch an one. Hath Chriſt then,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:153914:42"/> whom thou ſayeſt thou haſt received, hath he wrought Repentance, Mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, Sanctification in thine heart? Hath that Chriſt whom thou haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a crowne on his head, a Scepter in his hand, a throne in thine heart? doth he rule, and Lord it in thine heart, ſo as thine heart is ſwayed, and thy life ordered by his commands? If it be thus, then haſt thou indeed received Chriſt into thine heart. But this evidences it, that many have not received <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny beare the name of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and have taken up the profeſſion of his name, but yet they have not received him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their hearts. They have a <hi>Chriſt</hi> of their owne framing, a <hi>Chriſt</hi> forged in their owne fancy. What, not received <hi>Chriſt?</hi> Yes, God forbid but that they ſhould have received <hi>Chriſt</hi> with all their hearts. Well, looke a little upon the <hi>Chriſt</hi> they ſay they have received. Looke upon his head: Is their <hi>Chriſt</hi> crowned? Looke upon his hand, Is their <hi>Chriſt</hi> Sceptred? Look into their hearts, Is their <hi>Chriſt</hi> throned? What Lordſhip hath he? what dominion doth
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:153914:43"/> he exerciſe in their hearts? Not a whit, for all the <hi>Chriſt</hi> they have received, there is no Repentance, no Mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, no Holineſſe, no Obedience, for all the <hi>Chriſt</hi> they have received, they are earthly, covetous, full of uncleane luſts, drunkards, ſwearers, prophane and looſe. Be it knowne unto all ſuch that they have not received the <hi>Lords Chriſt,</hi> becauſe they have not received the Lord Chriſt. It is a falſe Chriſt they have received, It is the Libertins Chriſt, the carnall Goſpellers Chriſt, an Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomian Chriſt, a crownleſs, ſcepterleſs, throneleſs Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> I, but you doe us wrong, wee doe receive <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and hope, and deſire to be ſaved by him alone.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Nay, you doe <hi>Chriſt</hi> wrong: It is true indeed that you doe not ſay wee will not have this man to ſave us, to pardon us, to deliver us from hell, ſo you doe not refuſe him. But yet you ſay as thoſe wretches, <hi>Luk.</hi> 19. 14. <hi>Wee will not have this man to reigne over us:</hi> And thus you receive him not, thus you doe refuſe him; you put a reede into
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:153914:43"/> his hand, and a crown of thornes upon his head: Therefore it is a cleare caſe, that every impenitent, unſanctified, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient perſon doth not, hath not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Chriſt. Thou wilt receive him to ſave thee, but rule thee he ſhall not; Thou likeſt him for a <hi>Jeſus,</hi> but a <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> thou likeſt him not. <hi>Is Chriſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided?</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. This is to receive a <hi>divided Chriſt.</hi> They did wretchedly to part <hi>Chriſts</hi> Rayment, but they doe more wretchedly that will part, and divide <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, that will divide his <hi>Kingdom</hi> from his <hi>Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,</hi> that will receive him for a Saviour, but not a Prince, that will receive him an un-throned Prieſt. It is an whole Chriſt that muſt be received. He that receives not all, receives none at all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> By that, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 12. with <note place="margin">2.</note> verſe 16. <hi>To as many as received him.</hi> There were then that did receive him. How were they knowne? <hi>Of his fulneſſe wee have all received Grace for Grace.</hi> So then here are two things. <hi>Firſt,</hi> They that receive Chriſt, receive of his ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and are in their degree filled with
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:153914:44"/> Chriſt. They that receive Chriſt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of that, yea receive that in their meaſure which is in him: <hi>Of his fulneſſe wee receive. Secondly,</hi> they receive of his fulneſſe <hi>Grace for Grace,</hi> as the childe hath all parts anſwerable to his Father from whom he receives life, and being, as the waxe receives print for print, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to that which is in the ſeale. So that a man that receives Chriſt, not onely in the generall receives of that with which Chriſt is filled, but in his degree and meaſure receives of every grace that is in Chriſt. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 17. <hi>As he is, ſo are we</hi> in this world. All Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians that have received Chriſt in this world, are as he is, they have, and beare upon them the prints, ſtamps, impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the ſame graces that are in him. That as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeaks in another caſe, <hi>Prov.</hi> 27. 19. <hi>As in water face anſwers to face,</hi> ſo a Chriſtian receiving Chriſt, anſwers to him face to face, beares his Image, the ſtamp and impreſſion of his graces; for Chriſt once received, and entertained into the heart, is an aſſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating Chriſt, an altering, changing
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:153914:44"/> Chriſt, that turnes every ſoule into the likeneſſe of himſelfe. Chriſt wee ſaw before was received both by the eye and hand of faith. The receiving of Chriſt by the eye when he is indeed received, it works ſtrangely, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 18. The viſion of Chriſt by the eye of faith is a transforming viſion. As the bleſſed vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſt ſhall make us gloriouſly like him, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 2. <hi>Wee ſhall be like him, for wee ſhall ſee him as he is:</hi> So alſo the ſight of Chriſt by faith doth make us graciouſly like him, holy, heavenly, ſpirituall, full of goodneſſe, zeale, love, compaſſion, &amp;c. Now if the ſeeing of Chriſt by faith will work ſuch changes, ſuch aſſimilation, ſuch conformitie to Chriſt, what will then the receiving of him, and the taking him home into our hearts, and ſoules doe? How much more will that transforme a man into the Image of Chriſt? By this then may men be tryed whether they have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Chriſt or no. If thou have of Chriſts fulneſſe, if with <hi>Stephen, Act.</hi> 6. <hi>full of faith and the holy Ghoſt,</hi> if with the <hi>Romans, filled with knowledge and all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:153914:45"/> Rom.</hi> 15. 4. If as the <hi>Coloſsians, Col.</hi> 1. 9. then thou haſt received of Chriſts fulneſſe, and having received of his fulneſſe, thou haſt received Chriſt, for none can receive of his fulneſſe, till they have received him. If thou have in thee the Graces that are in Chriſt, Grace over againſt Grace, Meekneſſe, Humility, heavenly mindedneſſe, Love, &amp;c. which were in him; this Grace for Grace, argues that thou haſt received of his fulneſſe, and ſo haſt received him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. If thou be changed, conformed, and tranſformed to his Image, thou haſt received him. But this ſhews how many have not received him. They are full indeed, but of what are they full, and with what are they filled? They are full as they, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 29. as he <hi>Act.</hi> 5. 3. <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 10. full as they, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 14. <hi>eyes full of adultery,</hi> hearts full of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and earthlineſſe, heads full of wine and ſtrong drinke, mouthes full of oathes and curſing, hands full of bloud. Now is this the fulneſſe of Chriſt? Is this of the fulneſſe of Chriſt? or of the fulneſſe of the Devill? Have men againe
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:153914:45"/> received Grace for Grace? Chriſt was humble, they are proud; Chriſt was compaſſionate, they mercileſſe; Chriſt was loving, they are hatefull, and hating one another; Chriſt heavenly, and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, they earthly, and carnall, &amp;c. Is this Grace over againſt Grace? or vice or graceleſnes over againſt Grace? Art thou in this world like unto <hi>Chriſt?</hi> and did he live as thou now doſt? of Chriſt fulneſs therefore have not men received, neither yet have they received Chriſt himſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> They that receive Chriſt, <note place="margin">3.</note> receive him in that way, and in thoſe meanes wherein God offers him, yea and withall their hearts receive that wherein, and whereby Chriſt is recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. God offers Chriſt to be received in his Word, and the Miniſtry of the Goſpel. They that receive Chriſt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his Word, and in his Word doe receive him. A man that will receive Jewels, muſt receive the casket in which the Jewells are; hee that will receive ſuch gold and treaſure, muſt receive the purſe and the cheſt in which the gold
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:153914:46"/> and treaſure is. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 40. <hi>He that receives you, receives mee.</hi> And how are they received? <hi>verſ.</hi> 14. <hi>Whoſoever ſhall not receive you, nor heare your words.</hi> Therefore Chriſts Miniſters are recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved when their words are heard, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived; when the Word is received, the Miniſters are received, and when they are received, Chriſt is received. So here in the text; <hi>As yee have received Chriſt.</hi> How and when did they receive him? As yee have received Chriſt, and as <hi>yee have been taught,</hi> verſ. 7. they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him when they were taught by the miniſtry of the Word. Wee ſee <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 41. that ſome <hi>received the Word gladly.</hi> It was a good ſigne they received Chriſt, he that receives the Ordinance as that by which Chriſt is conveyed, and receives that truth in the Word in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his heart, that man receives Chriſt. Let men try themſelves by this. Is Gods Ordinance reſpected, and his truth received into thine heart? a good ſigne that Chriſt is received. But how many talke and brag of receiving <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that deſpiſe his ordinance, and reſiſt
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:153914:46"/> and reject that truth therein diſpenſed? Behold, to conclude againſt ſuch men, that they receive not Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> He that receives Chriſt, <note place="margin">4.</note> receives gladly all that belong to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> his Miniſters, his members, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 40. <hi>He that receives you, receives me;</hi> and ſo likewiſe he that receives mee, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives you. The <hi>Galatians</hi> had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Chriſt, and therefore ſee how <hi>Paul</hi> was received, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 14. <hi>Yee received me as an Angel of God, yea as Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> A ſigne they received Jeſus Chriſt. That as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes to <hi>Philemon</hi> of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſimus,</hi> Philem. 17. <hi>If thou count mee therefore a partner, receive him as my ſelfe.</hi> So ſayes Chriſt to all that receive him of his Miniſters, If you have received me, receive my Miniſters as my ſelfe. And ſo for his members, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 41. <hi>He that receiveth a Diſciple.</hi> He that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives Chriſt, receives a Diſciple, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives him into love, fellowſhip, and communion. When a man entertaines and receives a friend, he alſo entertaines and receives his ſervants. If the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants ſhould not be received, but be
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:153914:47"/> ſhut out, the Maſter would not thinke himſelfe heartily received of ſuch a man. Shall the triall be put upon this one thing? Judge then whether Chriſt be received by men in the world, by their receiving his Miniſters as his Miniſters, his members as his members. <hi>Yee ſuffer fooles gladly,</hi> ſayes <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 19. So men receive fooles, fidlers, jeſters, players; they receive good fellowes, gameſters, drunkards, ſwearers, &amp;c. Theſe men they receive gladly. But a Miniſter of Chriſt, and a member of Chriſt, as ſuch an one, how gladly is he received into our houſes, and compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies? As gladly as water is received in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſhip: mens contempt and ſcorne of theſe, teſtifies how they have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Thus much for the Argument, by which he preſſes to the duty. The <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> followes, <hi>So walke in him.</hi> By walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he meanes a going forward in the wayes of Godlineſſe, for walking is a progreſſive motion. Before wee come to the duty; firſt from the ſubjoyning this to the former, <hi>As yee have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:153914:47"/> Chriſt, ſo walke;</hi> learne thus much.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Whoſoever they are, that have indeed recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Chriſt, they doe walke in him.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THey that receive Chriſt, either in the Word, or in the Sacrament, they doe walke in him, that is, they doe in his ſtrength walke in obedience and fruitfulneſſe before God. True <hi>recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of</hi> Chriſt, are <hi>walkers in</hi> Chriſt, Chriſt truly received ſets men on walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. As faith hath <hi>an eye</hi> to ſee Chriſt, and his excellencies, as it hath <hi>an hand</hi> to reach out, and to receive Chriſt, ſo it hath alſo <hi>a foote</hi> to walke in Chriſt. It is in this caſe as it was in that <hi>Acts</hi> 3. in the healing of the creeple, one that was lame from his mothers wombe; He could not walke, but was carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. Now <hi>Peter</hi> cures this man; And how the cure was wrought, he tells them, <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. and 16. <hi>Why looke yee ſo earneſtly on us, as though by our owne power or holineſſe wee had made this man to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:153914:48"/> walke. The Name of Chriſt through faith in his Name, hath made this man ſtrong, yea the faith which is by him hath given him this perfect ſoundneſſe.</hi> It is ſaid, <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. <hi>That his ſeete and anckle-bones receiv'd ſtrength, and he leaping ſtood, and walked, and entred into the Temple, leaping and walking.</hi> So then the creeple by faith receiving Chriſt into his heart, <hi>ver.</hi> 16. doth receive ſtrength into his limbes to leape, and walke, yea ſo as verſ. 9. <hi>All the people ſaw him walking.</hi> Now juſt ſo it is ſpiritually with all that receive Chriſt. Though before they were er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant creeples, creeples from the wombe, that could not ſtirre one foote in the wayes of God, yet when once by faith they receive Chriſt into their hearts, the feete &amp; anckle-bones of their ſoules immediately receive ſtrength, and they preſently fall to walking, ſo that all the people may ſee them walking, doing thoſe duties, performing that ſervice and obedience, which before they did not. There was another creeple hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>Acts</hi> 14. 8. who was a <hi>creeple from his mothers wombe, who had never walked.</hi>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:153914:48"/> He heares <hi>Paul</hi> preach, verſ. 9. <hi>Paul</hi> ſees that he had faith in him to be healed, and thereupon bids him ſtand upon his feete, <hi>And he leaped and walked,</hi> ver. 10. So it is true ſpiritually, though a man have been a creeple all his dayes, one that never walked, never did any duty of obedience ſince he was borne, yet when once a man hath faith, and by faith hath received Chriſt: Chriſt by faith received will make ſuch an one walke, as never walked before. Wee ſhall ſee that amongſt other things our Saviour did, it was uſually one thing with him to <hi>heale the lame,</hi> and to ſet them <hi>on walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> Mat. 15. 30, 31. And <hi>Mat.</hi> 21. 14. The miracles, and cures that Chriſt wrought upon mens bodies, were but to teach what a Chriſt he ſhould be ſpiritually to mens ſoules. It taught that Chriſt received into the ſoule ſhould preſently cure the lameneſſe thereof, and being once received hee makes lame ſoules walke, that never walked before. So <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 1. <hi>There is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> When we are in Chriſt, then he
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:153914:49"/> is in us; Then he is in us, and wee are in him when wee receive him. But what kinde of perſons are they that are in Chriſt, and Chriſt in them, that have received Chriſt, who walke after the Spirit? Therefore where Chriſt is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, he ſets men a walking in the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of holineſſe, and obedience. When wee receive Chriſt, as he abides in us, ſo we abide in him. Now when a man hath received Chriſt, ſo as he abides in him, what will that man doe? See 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. 6. <hi>He that ſayes he abides in him, ought himſelfe alſo to walke.</hi> And how muſt he walke? <hi>Even as he walked.</hi> Chriſt was a walking Chriſt, and ſo every Chriſtian that hath received Chriſt, muſt be a walking Chriſtian. And muſt, and will walke in that way in which <hi>Chriſt</hi> wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. And the reaſons of this are two.</p>
               <p>Firſt, That 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 12. <hi>He that hath</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1.</note> 
                  <hi>the Son hath life, he that hath not the Son hath not life.</hi> He that receives the Son receives life, life from Chriſt cannot be idle, and aſleepe, but it is active, ſtirring, and full of motion. Where Chriſt is received, ſpirituall life is received, and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:153914:49"/> ſpirituall life will ſet a man awalking, and aworking. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 25. <hi>If wee live in the Spirit, let us alſo walke in the Spirit;</hi> So that where there is <hi>ſpirituall life,</hi> there is <hi>ſpirituall walking.</hi> And where Chriſt is received there is ſpirituall life, <hi>for he that hath the Son hath life,</hi> And he that hath received the Sonne <hi>hath the Sonne;</hi> for wee come to have him by receiving of him. It is poſſible that in nature a man may have life, and yet not walke, but where ſpirituall life is, there will be walking. Chriſt received, lives in us, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 20. And as he lives, ſo he walkes in us, and makes us walke in him.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Becauſe Chriſt being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, the Spirit of God is received al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, as we ſaw before. Now, the Spirit of God being received, he will make us walke in duties of obedience <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36. 27. <hi>I will put my Spirit within you, and cauſe you to walke in my ſtatutes.</hi> Chriſt received, the Spirit is received; the Spirit received cauſes a man to walke, ſo that where Chriſt is received, a man muſt needs walke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:153914:50"/>
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Trialls</hi> of Mens Receiving of Chriſt.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>BY this, may men try themſelves, whether they have received Chriſt or not. Men heare the Goſpel daily Preached unto them, and live under the Miniſtry of the Word in which Chriſt is offered unto them. Doe they receive Chriſt thus offered them? yes that they doe by all meanes, if you will beleeve them. Men frequently receive the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and not one receives, but he hopes he receives Chriſt into his heart. Now it deeply concernes us ſeriouſly to examine our ſelves whether in truth we have received Chriſt or no, after ſo much uſe of his Ordinances. If under ſo much Preaching, and after ſo much receiving the Sacrament, wee have not received Chriſt, we are in a miſerable condition. Let us therefore after ſo much hearing, and receiving, examine our ſelves whether wee have received Chriſt, or not. How ſhall wee then know it? This is a ſure thing, where
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:153914:50"/> Chriſt is received it will be ſeene, and may be diſcerned. Wee ſhall ſee <hi>Mar.</hi> 7. 24. that Chriſt entred into a houſe, and would have no man know it, but, ſays the Text, <hi>he could not be hid.</hi> Where ever Chriſt is then, he cannot be hid. He could not be hid in the houſe into which he was received, but he was heard of, he was ſeene, and taken notice of. And if he could not be hid in the houſe into which he was received, then much leſſe can he be hid in the heart into which he is received. It is a thouſand times eaſier to hide him in an houſe, then to hide him in an heart. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ye have received Chriſt, he cannot be hid; Why ſo? Becauſe where he is received, he ſets men awalking in him, and in the wayes of godlineſſe. Well then, If wee walke in Chriſt, if we walke in obedience to Gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements, if we walke holily, and religiouſly, then here is matter of ſweet comfort unto us. Certainly, ſuch as walke in Chriſt, have received him. As wee cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him, but wee muſt walke in him, ſo wee cannot walke in him, but wee
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:153914:51"/> muſt receive him. Our walking in him is an infallible evidence of our recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him. But on the contrary, this ſhews how few have received Chriſt in the Word and Sacrament, becauſe ſo few doe walke in him. Doe but conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what your walking is. Doe not men walke as <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 2. <hi>Yee walked accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the courſe of this world, according to the Prince of the power of the ayre, the ſpirit that now workes in the children of diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</hi> Doe not men walke as <hi>Epbeſ.</hi> 4. 17, 18. <hi>As the Gentiles walke in the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of their mindes, having their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding darkened, &amp;c.</hi> Doe not many walke as they, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 18, 19. <hi>Many walke who are the enemies of the Croſſe, whoſe God is their belly, who minde earthly things.</hi> Doe not many walke, as 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 3. <hi>When wee walked in laſciviouſneſſe, luſts, exceſſe of wine, revellings, banquet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, and abominable Idolatries.</hi> Doe not many walke in theſe walkes, and yet talke of receiving Chriſt? In Gods feare, judge whether ſuch walking, be walking in Chriſt. Call yee walking in the luſts of the fleſh, the luſts of the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:153914:51"/> world, the luſts of the devill, call yee this a walking in Chriſt? If wee would profeſſedly walke out of Chriſt, what would we, or could we doe other? Lay together <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 17, 18. with 20, 21. If ſuch walkers have not in truth lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Chriſt, then have not ſuch walkers in truth received Chriſt. Let ſuch wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers in their conſciences judge whether ſuch walking be walking in Chriſt, or in Satan. And doe they that receive <hi>Chriſt,</hi> walke in Satan? Let all ſuch know once for all, that all their hearing, and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Sacrament notwithſtanding they have not received Chriſt. A walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Chriſt, will prove a receiving of Chriſt, if no walking in him, then no receiving of him.</p>
               <p>Now more particularly for the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. <hi>Walking,</hi> that is going on, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in duties of Religion, and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and walking <hi>in him,</hi> that is, by his power, and ſtrength, or <hi>in him,</hi> that is, according to his will, or patterne. Learne hence;</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:153914:52"/>
               <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>It is a Chriſtians duty to <hi>walke in Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>IT is the duty of a Chriſtian to walke,</hi> to be in motion, in a progreſſive motion, and going forwards. A Chriſtian muſt not be a talker, a talker onely, but he muſt be a walker. It is eaſie to talke of Chriſt, though that be more then many will doe, but it is not ſo eaſie, nor ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary to walke in him. It is a good ſigne of a mans being in Chriſt. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 1. <hi>No condemnation to ſuch as are in him.</hi> But how may they be knowne that are in him? <hi>They walke after</hi> the Spirit.</p>
               <p>It is a ſure ſigne, and evidence of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall life. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 25. <hi>If wee live in the ſpirit, let us alſo walke in the ſpirit.</hi> If we ſee a man walk, we are ſure he is alive.</p>
               <p>It is a ſigne a man is in ſpirituall health. <hi>Ariſe,</hi> ſayes Chriſt to the pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey man, <hi>Take up thy bed and walke,</hi> Luk. 5. It was a ſigne he was healed when he could walke.</p>
               <p>Sick men that keepe their beds, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not walke. It is a ſigne that men have
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:153914:52"/> their ſpirituall ſight, and limbes, when they can walke. The lame, and the blind, cannot walke. Ignorant perſons are blinde. Men that are bodily blinde, can and doe walke, but it is impoſſible for men ſpiritually blinde to walke, becauſe it is impoſſible to walke but in the way, and impoſſible to walke in the way, when it is not ſeene. And lame perſons wanting limbes, and legges, as blinde perſons want eyes, neither can they walke, but when men walke, it is a ſure ſigne that they have their eyes, their legges, their health, and ſpirituall life.</p>
               <p>It is a ſigne of ſpirituall ſtrength. A childe hath life but cannot walke, becauſe it is weake, and wants ſtrength, but as it growes ſtrong, ſo it gets abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie to walke. And when a childe can once walke, it is a ſigne it hath natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſtrength. So here, if wee have ſome ſeedes, and beginnings of ſpirituall life, yet wee are but babes, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme weaklings, till wee can walke. But when once wee doe walke, it is a ſigne that wee are growne in grace,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:153914:53"/> and have gotten ſome meaſure of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſtrength. <hi>Zech.</hi> 10. 12. <hi>I will ſtrengthen him in the Lord, and they ſhall walke up and downe in his Name.</hi> When therefore men walke up and downe in the name of the Lord, it is a ſigne they are ſtrengthened in the Lord.</p>
               <p>It is a ſigne of Communion with God, and benefit received in the uſe of his Ordinances, the Word and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Gen.</hi> 29. 1. <hi>Then Jacob lifted up his feete, and walked, and went on his jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney;</hi> Then, namely after the ſweet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion he had with GOD in <hi>Bethel.</hi> And ſo when wee lift up our feete, and walke, with renewed vigour, and ſtrength, it is a ſigne wee have had fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with God in his Word, and Sacrament. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2. 3. <hi>Hee will teach us his wayes, and wee will walke in his pathes.</hi> It is a ſigne that God himſelfe hath had the teaching of us, and that in the Miniſtry of the Word, wee have had communion with him when once wee fall awalking. So here in the Text, <hi>walking</hi> in Chriſt is made an evidence of <hi>Receiving</hi> Chriſt. Then may a man
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:153914:53"/> be knowne to have received Chriſt in the Word and Sacrament, when upon theſe duties done a man ſets to walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>It condemnes ſuch as will be Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, <note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note> but walke not. The world is full of talkers, but walkers are rare to be found. Religion muſt be in the tongue, &amp; it is that ſhould be talked of, though many men are more aſhamed to have holy &amp; good ſpeech come from them, then to have oathes, and filthy commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication fall from their mouthes. I do not condemne talking of Chriſt, talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Religion; Talke and ſpare not, but yet walke withall, adde walking to your talking, and then are yee right Chriſtians indeed. Set your feete on worke as well as your tongues, and then yee ſhall bridle the tongues of ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. It condemnes alſo Sedentary Chriſtians, that ſet them downe, and ſit ſtill. Sitting is for heaven. That is the <hi>Reſt that remaines for the people of God.</hi> But this life is no <hi>Reſting,</hi> but a <hi>walking</hi> life. Wee muſt not thinke of ſitting, till wee come to <hi>ſit upon thrones,</hi>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:153914:54"/> till wee come to <hi>ſit downe with Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Iſaac, and Jacob in the Kingdome of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It condemnes alſo ſuch kinde of Chriſtians that have ſometimes ſome fits of goodneſſe, but goe not on. They have their good words, but they are ſoone over. This is not to walke; walking is a conſtant continued pace in good. A thiefe may ſometimes walke on in the high way, but he will not ſtay long in it, but quickly turnes aſide into one by-way or other; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the honeſt traveller keepes on, and goes on an end till he comes to his journeys end. It is one thing to walke on in the wayes of God, and another thing to take a few ſteps, and out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Such are no walkers. A godly man who for his ſetled courſe walkes on in the wayes of obedience, may ſometimes through tentation, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity, ſtep aſide into the wayes of ſinne, yet for all that he cannot be ſaid to walke in thoſe wayes. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1. 1. <hi>Hee walkes not in the counſell of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly.</hi> And ſo a morall or a wicked
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:153914:54"/> man, may ſometimes be in a good du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or a good way, but yet becauſe his conſtant courſe bends, and goes ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, he cannot be ſaid to walke in the wayes of God.</p>
               <p>And ſo much for the firſt thing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted unto. The ſecond followes. To be <hi>Rooted</hi> in Chriſt, to a ſtabilitie, and ſtedfaſtneſſe in the profeſſion of Chriſt, <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. <hi>Rooted in him.</hi> It is a metaphor taken from trees. Trees have no ſtabilitie, nor firmeneſſe, unleſſe they roote into firme earth, neither have wee any firmeneſſe, unleſſe wee roote deepe in Chriſt. The point wee learne hence is this:</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>It is not enough for a Chriſtian to profeſſe, and beare the Name of Chriſt, but he muſt be <hi>Rooted</hi> in him.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>CHriſtians muſt be <hi>Rooted</hi> Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: Chriſt is the ſoyle of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſoule, and a Chriſtian ſoule muſt Roote in this ſoyle. That looke as <hi>Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dad</hi>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:153914:55"/> ſpeakes in another caſe of a wicked mans outward eſtate, and flouriſhing in the world, <hi>Job</hi> 8. 17. <hi>His rootes are wrapped about the heape, and ſees the place of ſtones;</hi> that is, he rootes deeply, and ſpreads about his roots, like a tree that hath its roots folded in the earth, and whoſe roots run in amongſt the ſtones, ſo ſhould it be with a Chriſtian: Hee ſhould ſo roote into Chriſt, that his rootes ſhould wrap about the heape, wrap about Chriſt, he ſhould have a folded roote in Chriſt. Chriſt is a Roote, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 12. 16. <hi>I am the Roote and off-ſpring of David,</hi> the Roote, and Branch of <hi>David.</hi> How can Chriſt be both Roote and Branch? Wee reade of the <hi>Roote of Jeſſe,</hi> Iſa. 11. 1. And Chriſt is called the <hi>Branch,</hi> Zech. 6. 12. <hi>Behold the man whoſe name is the Branch.</hi> If <hi>David</hi> then be Chriſts Roote, and Chriſt his Branch, how is Chriſt the Roote of <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>David</hi> and all the faithfull his Branches? <hi>Joh.</hi> 15. 1. <hi>I am the Vine,</hi> the Vine-roote, <hi>and yee are the Branches?</hi> And yet both theſe are true; That Chriſt is both the Roote, and
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:153914:55"/> Branch of <hi>David.</hi> Take him in his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature, according to the fleſh, and he is the <hi>Branch</hi> of <hi>David,</hi> for he was made of the ſeed of <hi>David,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the fleſh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 3. But conſider him in both natures joyntly in one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and ſo he is the <hi>Roote of David,</hi> and of all the faithfull. And as he is the Roote, ſo ſhould all the faithfull roote themſelves into this Roote, <hi>Rooted in him.</hi> He is the Roote into which all true Chriſtians muſt root themſelves. And that upon theſe reaſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> All true Chriſtians muſt grow. It is that which is often called for in Scripture. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 18. <hi>Grow in Grace.</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 2. that yee may grow. There is nothing that doth more evidence the truth of Grace, then the growth. Then a Chriſtian may have good evidence that he is a true Chriſtian, when he is a growing Chriſtian. And a man that growes not in Grace, and goodneſſe, may juſtly queſtion the truth of his Grace and goodneſſe, the truth of his Chriſtianitie. So that it much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes a Chriſtian to grow. Now looke
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:153914:56"/> how much it concernes a Chriſtian to be a growing Chriſtian, ſo much it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes him to be a Rooted Chriſtian, to be Rooted in Chriſt. Becauſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe a man be rooted in Chriſt, it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible he ſhould grow. Wee ſee in nature that plants and trees firſt roote before they grow, and their growth followes after their rooting. So much appeares by that compariſon, <hi>Job</hi> 8. 16, 17. <hi>He is greene, and his branches ſhoote.</hi> And this comes from that which followes, <hi>His roots are wrapped about the heape.</hi> Hee rootes, and therefore hee ſhoots. A tree cannot ſhoote till it roote. So <hi>Jer.</hi> 12. 2. the Prophet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring wicked men to trees, <hi>Thou haſt,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>planted them, yea they have taken roote, they grow.</hi> But firſt take roote, and then grow. So Chriſtians muſt grow, but yet before they can grow, they muſt firſt be planted, and take root. GOD promiſes to make his Church grow, and her branches to ſpread, but withall he promiſes to make her roote. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14. 5, 6. <hi>I will be as the dew unto Iſrael, he ſhall grow as the Lilly, and caſt
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:153914:56"/> forth his roots as Lebanon, his branches ſhall ſpread, &amp;c.</hi> Never can a Chriſtian grow as a Lilly, though he be under daily dewes, nor his branches ſpread, unleſſe he caſt forth his roots as <hi>Leba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non,</hi> as the trees, and Cedars of <hi>Leba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non.</hi> What are dewes without Roots? <hi>My Doctrine,</hi> ſayes <hi>Moſes, ſhall drop as the raine, my ſpeech ſhall diſtill as the dew. Deut.</hi> 32. 2. Though a man live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the dew of the Miniſtry, which is a good meanes of growth, yet if he want a Roote in Chriſt, he will never grow. The deeper a tree is rooted, the more it growes. The greater the roote, the deeper, and wider it ſpreads it ſelfe, the greater is the properity of that tree. A buſh growes, but growes not to the height that a Cedar doth, nor to the greatneſſe an Oake doth, becauſe the roote of a buſh is but ſmall. It rootes not as an Oake, as a Cedar, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore riſes not, ſpreads not as doth an Oake, or a Cedar. Wee ſee divers ſizes of Chriſtians, ſome greater, ſome leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, ſome higher, ſome lower trees of Righteouſneſſe. What may the reaſon
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:153914:57"/> of it be? Are they not all ſet, and plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the ſame ſoyle? Is it not the ſame Chriſt that feeds and nouriſhes them all? It is ſo, and yet theſe trees though all ſet in the ſame ſoyle, all fed by the ſame ſap, yet are they not all of the ſame height and bigneſſe: And the reaſon is, becauſe they all roote not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like. Some roote deeper then others, ſome ſpread out their rootes further then others, and as every one rootes, ſo every one growes. See how the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt ſpeakes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 80. 9, 10. of that vine. <hi>It filled the land, the hills were co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with the ſhadow of it, the boughes thereof were like the goodly Cedars, &amp;c.</hi> And all came from this, <hi>Thou cauſedſt it to take deepe roote.</hi> So that the deeper roote, the greater growth; And ſo in this caſe, the deeper roote wee take in Chriſt, the greater growth wee have in Chriſt, and grace. In as much then as every Chriſtian is bound to grow, and there is no growth without a roote, therefore muſt every Chriſtian roote in Chriſt. Every Chriſtian is bound to <hi>grow exceedingly,</hi> 2 Theſ. 3. there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:153914:57"/> it concernes a Chriſtian not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be rooted, but to be deeply roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in CHRIST, becauſe ſo as wee roote, ſo wee grow proportionably. The deeper roote, the greater and fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer growth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> All true Chriſtians muſt <note place="margin">2.</note> beare fruit. What called for more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently? <hi>Matth.</hi> 3. <hi>Bring forth fruit.</hi> Hereby wee glorifie God, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15. 8. Hereby wee give evidence that wee are Chriſts Diſciples, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15. 8. Hereby wee give evidence of our union with Chriſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15. 5. It is a dangerous thing not to bring forth fruit, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15. 2. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. 10. A matter therefore of great neceſſitie to bring forth fruit. Now it is impoſſible to bring forth the fruits of grace, and the ſpirit, unleſſe wee be rooted in Chriſt. In nature no roote no fruite. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 9. 16. <hi>Their roote is dryed up, they ſhall beare no fruit.</hi> There muſt be a roote before there can be fruite; as <hi>Jer.</hi> 12. 2. <hi>Thou haſt planted them, they have taken roote, they bring forth fruit;</hi> but firſt, have taken roote. And that ſpeech ſhewes as much,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:153914:58"/> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 19. 30. <hi>They ſhall yet againe take roote downward, and bring forth fruit up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</hi> So it is in this caſe: No ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all roote, no ſpirituall fruite. <hi>Jude</hi> 12. <hi>Trees without fruit, pluckt up by the roots.</hi> What wonder that they were <hi>fruitleſſe,</hi> when they were <hi>rootleſs?</hi> they muſt needs be without fruit, when they were with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out roote. On the contrary, a godly man he is fruitfull, becauſe he is roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Chriſt, and therefore fruited, becauſe rooted. <hi>Jer.</hi> 17. 8. <hi>He is a tree that brings forth fruit in a time of drought, in a time of heate, he is fruitfull.</hi> And marke whence it comes, <hi>He ſhall be as a tree planted by the</hi> waters, that ſpreads out her roots by the river. He is roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Chriſt, and therefore fruited by Chriſt. To which purpoſe wee may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude to that, <hi>Prov.</hi> 12. 12. <hi>The roote of the righteous yeeldeth fruit.</hi> It is not the <hi>Branch</hi> of the righteous that yeelds fruit, but it is the <hi>roote.</hi> It is Chriſt who is the roote of a righteous man, and when a man is rooted in him he yeelds fruite. It is impoſſible for a branch without a roote to bring forth
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:153914:58"/> fruite. That was a miraculous, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary caſe, that <hi>Aarons</hi> rod cut off from the ſtock, and without a roote, did bring forth buds, and bloſſomes, and yeelded Almonds. But in ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry courſe it is a thing impoſſible. It is impoſſible for us to bring forth Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, Grapes, or any fruite, unleſſe wee be rooted in Chriſt. All fruite is from Chriſt the roote. <hi>Philip.</hi> 1. 11. <hi>The fruits of holineſſe and righteouſneſſe which are by Chriſt.</hi> So that then there being a neceſſitie that a Chriſtian bring forth fruite, and that there can be no fruite, unleſſe he be rooted in Chriſt, it is therefore a thing of abſolute ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie, that a Chriſtian be rooted in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> A Chriſtian muſt perſevere, <note place="margin">3.</note> and be ſtable in the truth, muſt hold out, and continue. It is ſtill called for, <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 23. The promiſe of ſalvation is made to ſuch as perſevere. <hi>He that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeveres to the end ſhall be ſaved,</hi> Mat. 24. It is made the note of a true Chriſtian, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8. 30. And it is that which at the laſt day will fill our hearts with infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:153914:59"/> comfort, and confidence, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. 28. Now it is impoſſible a man ſhould perſevere, and continue, unleſſe he be rooted in Chriſt. Boughes pluckt off from trees, being ſet in water, may looke freſh and greene for two or three dayes, but becauſe they have no roote, they quickly decay, and dye. A ſtake, or a poſt is pitched in the ground, but yet becauſe it hath no roote, it is eaſie to wriggle, and plucke it up, and carry it whither one will. But now it is not ſo with a great tree, there a man may tug, and plucke with all his might, and not get it up. Set a teame of horſe to an oake, and they cannot ſtirre, nor move it. And what is the reaſon of this difference, but becauſe the tree hath a roote that fixes, and faſtens it in the earth, and the ſtake or poſt hath none? The ſtony ground made a faire ſhew, it ſprang quickly, gave faire and good hopes, but yet it came to nothing, but ſoone vaniſht; and what might the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be? See <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. 6. 20. 21. <hi>Luk.</hi> 8. 13. want of roote was their bane, they had no roote in Chriſt, and
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:153914:59"/> therefore endured not. The tree that is rooted, though heate and drought come, yet ceaſes not yeelding fruite. <hi>Jer.</hi> 17. 8. Let a man make never ſo faire a profeſſion of faith, love, zeale, &amp;c. yet if that man be not rooted in Chriſt, that man will wither, vaniſh, and come to nothing, ſpecially if the Sunne ariſe, and there come a time of heate. It is ſaid of a righteous man, <hi>Prov.</hi> 10. 25. <hi>That he is an everlaſting foundation,</hi> he ſtirres not, moves not, is not a reede ſhaken with the winde. How comes it about that neither here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, nor perſecutions, one thing nor another ſtirres him, but he is immove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able? See <hi>Prov.</hi> 12. 3. <hi>The roote of the righteous ſhall not be moved,</hi> he hath a roote, hee is rooted in Chriſt, and therefore is not moved. So here the Apoſtles drift is to perſwade the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſsians</hi> to perſeverance, and exhorting them thereunto, he wiſhes them <hi>to be rooted in Chriſt.</hi> So that in as much as Chriſtians ought to perſevere, and that cannot be done unleſſe a man be rooted in Chriſt, it is therefore of
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:153914:60"/> neceſſitie, that a man bee rooted in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> See what the Apoſtle ſayes <note place="margin">4.</note> 
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. 14. <hi>Wee are made partakers of Chriſt.</hi> That is a precious bleſſing: It ſhould be the ayme of every Chriſtian. And indeed a man is no Chriſtian in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede till hee be made a partaker of Chriſt. Wee come to the Lords Table for this end to be partakers of Chriſt. Now we cannot be partakers of Chriſt, till wee be rooted in Chriſt. There is no participation of Chriſt, till there be a Radication in Chriſt. No parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation of Chriſt in the Sacrament, till rooted in him. A man may come to the Sacrament, and partake of Bread and Wine, may bee partaker of the Lords Table, and yet if he be not roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Chriſt, partakes not of Chriſt. Herbes and trees are partakers of the heart, of the ſtrength, of the fat of the earth, and the moyſture thereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are rooted in the earth. So by beeing rooted in Chriſt, wee come to be partakers of him. See that ſame <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 17. <hi>Thou wert graffed in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:153914:60"/> them, and with them partakeſt of the roote and fatneſſe of the Olive.</hi> When a cience is ingraffed into an Olive, it partakes of the fatneſſe of the Olive; But how? It firſt partakes of the root. The Olive hath a roote, by that it par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes of the fatneſſe of the earth, and the branches by having that roote for their roote, are made partakers of that fatneſſe. There is a fatneſſe, a ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in Chriſt, and a fatneſſe and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in Gods Ordinances, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63. 5. Now when we come to the Sacrament, wee deſire to be made partakers of the fatneſſe and ſweetneſſe of Chriſt: firſt then be rooted in him, and we ſhall be made partakers of him, and his ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Many receive the Sacrament that are not partakers of Chriſt, and all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they be not rooted in him. Thou that commeſt to the Sacrament before thou be rooted in Chriſt, art an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy receiver. Wee have no right to the Sacrament, till wee be rooted in Chriſt. So that as we deſire to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy receivers of the Sacrament, ſo it concernes us to be rooted in Chriſt.
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:153914:61"/> We know the danger of unworthy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving. Hee that in receiving is not made partaker of Chriſt, receives un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily. He that is not firſt rooted in him, cannot be partaker of him. A rootleſſe receiver is a fruitleſſe recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; a fruitleſſe receiver is an unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy receiver. He that hath a roote, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives <hi>good</hi> by the Sacrament, hee that hath not a roote, receives <hi>hurt</hi> by it. Take a tree that hath a roote, and ſet it in the earth, and the moyſture and fat of the earth nouriſhes and feedes it. But take a ſticke or a ſtake that hath no roote, and drive it into the earth, and the fat and moyſture of the earth rottes it. To come to the Sacrament having a Roote will make our ſoules thrive, but to come to the Sacrament without a Roote, will rotte and bane our ſoules. As therefore wee deſire at any time, but ſpecially at the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, to be partakers of Chriſt, ſo firſt get wee our ſelves rooted into him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> and laſtly, That ſame is a <note place="margin">5.</note> terrible Imprecation of <hi>Davids</hi> againſt
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:153914:61"/> 
                  <hi>Doeg,</hi> Pſal. 52. 5. <hi>God ſhall</hi> roote <hi>thee out of the land</hi> of the living. It is hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vieſt in a ſpirituall ſenſe, as Heaven is the land of the living. And yet as heavie as it is, it will be the porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all ſuch as are not rooted in Chriſt. God will roote out all ſuch out of the land of the living. As wee would be rooted in the land of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, ſo get wee our ſelves rooted in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Labour wee therefore to get our ſelves rooted, and deeply rooted in <note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe 1.</note> Chriſt. Men of the world doe ſeeke to take roote in their kinde, and to ſpread their rootes in the earth. <hi>Job</hi> 5. 3. <hi>I have ſeene the fooliſh taking roote. Jer.</hi> 12. 2. <hi>Thou haſt planted them, they have taken roote.</hi> What a doe to roote themſelves in a ſoyle, out of which they ſhall be pluckt up by the rootes? <hi>Job</hi> 5. 3. <hi>I have ſeene the fooliſh taking roote, but ſuddenly I have curſed his habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</hi> It fares with them as with the curſed figtree, <hi>Mark.</hi> 11. 20. As they paſſed by they <hi>ſaw the figge tree dryed up from the roots.</hi> But alas how few take
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:153914:62"/> care for Rooting in Chriſt Jeſus, and for a bleſſed Radication in him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>What is to be done that wee may get our ſelves rooted in Chriſt?</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>FIrſt,</hi> and principally get faith in Chriſt. There be other things that helpe a Chriſtian to roote deeper into Chriſt when hee is once rooted; but faith is the firſt thing that muſt roote a man into Chriſt. So here in the Text; <hi>Rooted and built up in him.</hi> But how? <hi>ſtabliſhed in the faith,</hi> not onely in the doctrine of faith, but in the grace of faith. Now faith doth three things to a mans rooting in Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Faith plucks him up by the roots out of the ſoyle of nature. A man that will have a tree roote in his Garden, in his Orchard, muſt firſt have it pluckt up by the rootes out of the hedge, or wood, and common, where it natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly growes. It cannot roote in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, ſo long as it ſtands rooted in the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:153914:62"/> wood. So a man cannot roote in Chriſt, ſo long as hee is rooted in the ſoyle of nature, of meere moralitie and civilitie. Hee muſt firſt be fetcht up by the very rootes, out of that curſed foyle. Now faith is that which doth it: faith is that which drawes us up by the Rootes out of the hedge, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of Nature. In a miraculous caſe it is poſſible to plucke up a tree by the Rootes. <hi>Luk.</hi> 17. 6. <hi>Yee might ſay unto this Sycamore tree, Be thou plucked up by the rootes, and it ſhould obey you.</hi> But when may a man ſo ſay? <hi>If you have faith as a graine of muſtard-ſeede.</hi> Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous faith then could plucke up trees by the roots. So it is alſo with juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying faith. Before wee can be rooted in Chriſt, wee muſt be un-rooted, and up-rooted in regard of our naturall condition, as before the Sycamore can be planted in the Sea, it muſt firſt be pluckt up by the roots. Now juſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faith is that which pluckes up theſe wilde Sycamores, and wilde olives by the rootes. A man is pluckt up by the rootes when he denies himſelfe, when
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:153914:63"/> he goes out of himſelfe, when he comes off from all bottome, he hath in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and in Nature. Now faith is that which makes a man deny himſelfe, goe out of himſelfe, and thus un-roote himſelfe. See how <hi>Paul</hi> pluckes up his Phariſaiſme, and all his civill legall righteouſneſſe by the very Rootes, and that by the ſelfe-denyall of faith. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 4, 8. If any man elſe may grow up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his owne roote, then much more I, for thus and thus am I rooted, of the roote of Iſrael, a naturall Hebrew, a circumciſed Hebrew, a Phariſee, a ſtrict and zealous profeſſor of Jewiſh Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and for legall righteouſneſſe, a man before men unblameable, and yet I denyed my ſelfe, pluckt up my ſelfe from all theſe rootes, counted all loſſe and dung, to be found rooted in Chriſt. Faith is a ſelfe-denying grace, and drags a man up by the roots out of his natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall condition.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Faith implants a man into the ſoyle of grace, it implants a man into Chriſt. When a tree is pluckt up by the roots, yet if it be not ſet into the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:153914:63"/> earth, in the Garden, or Orchyard, it rootes not there. The way to have it to roote in the Garden is, after it is pluckt up by the rootes to ſet it in the ground, and ſet it in the earth. There muſt bee a planting of a tree before there can be a rooting. <hi>Jer.</hi> 12. 2. <hi>Thou haſt planted them, they have taken roote,</hi> therefore before taking roote, there muſt be a planting. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 80. 8, 9. <hi>Thou haſt planted the Vine, thou haſt cauſed it to take deepe roote.</hi> So it is here, before there can be rooting in Chriſt, there muſt be a planting in him. Now faith is that which plants us in Chriſt. That ſets us, put us into Chriſt, the ſoyle in which we muſt roote. The Apoſtle hath a phraſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 5. of <hi>being plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into Chriſts death.</hi> There is a plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into his death, and there is a plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into his perſon. When a tree is ſet into the earth, then it is planted, when a man is ſet into Chriſt, and is in him, then is a man planted in him. Now by faith it is that we are <hi>in Chriſt, Phil.</hi> 3. <hi>That I may be found in him, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the righteouſneſſe of faith.</hi> And thus
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:153914:64"/> faith implanting us into Chriſt, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and ſetting us into the ſoyle, doth roote us into Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Faith ſuckes, attracts, and drawes nouriſhment from Chriſt. If a tree be ſet into the ground, yet if it draw not moyſture, heart and nouriſhment out of the ground, it roots not, but by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees will dye. But when it is once ſet into the ground, and faſtned there, and doth draw ſap, and moyſture out of the earth, then the roote runs and ſpreads this way, and that way, and ſo the tree radicates to the purpoſe. So then a Chriſtian being planted in Chriſt, doth roote in him, when there is a quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, nouriſhing ſap drawne out of him into a mans foule, that makes it ſpring and ſpread it ſelfe into Chriſt. Now faith is that which drawes, ſuckes, and extracts vertue &amp; power out of Chriſt, which makes us ſpread, and roote in him. Thus by theſe things, faith roots us into Chriſt. So that if wee would roote in Chriſt, wee muſt get faith in Chriſt, and the more faith we get, the greater and deeper roote ſhall we have in Chriſt.</p>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:153914:64"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Get repentance, and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification. <note place="margin">2.</note> When once a man hath got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten into Chriſt, and is begun by faith to be rooted in him, theſe will exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly helpe to make a man roote more deeply, and to ſpread abroad his roote in Chriſt. The more ſinnes and luſts wee nouriſh in our hearts, the leſſe we roote in Chriſt. Chriſt is indeed a fat, and a fertile ſoyle, but though a tree, or herbes be planted in fat, and good ground, yet a man may ſo order the matter, that herbes and trees ſhall root but poorely in it; for let a man mingle with it barren and baggage cold earth, or throw in gravell, ſtones, or flints in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the earth, and about the roots, and theſe will hinder the rooting of a tree. So though Chriſt be a fat ſoyle, yet if wee ſuffer our ſinnes, and our luſts to lodge in our hearts, theſe will hinder our rooting in Chriſt. But theſe remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and taken away, it will conduce ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly to our rooting. Now repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and mortification, theſe take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and remove ſins and luſts. When God planted a Vineyard, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5. it was
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:153914:65"/> his purpoſe that it ſhould roote, and it did roote. <hi>Pſal. 80. 9. Thou cauſedſt it to take deepe roote.</hi> I, but marke what courſe God did take. <hi>Iſa. 5. 2. He fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced it, he gathered out the ſtones.</hi> He clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and rid the ſoyle of all ſuch hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full things as might hinder the root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof. And ſo gathering out the ſtones, it did take deepe roote. Now repentance doth this, it takes away the ſtones out of the heart, it takes away the heart of ſtone, and ſo makes way for rooting. If a man be in Chriſt, and yet have an heart of ſtone, there bee ſtones in the ſoyle, but repentance ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away the heart of ſtone, fits us for rooting, and ſpreading. Againe, ſet herbes in a rich, and fat ſoyle, yet if that ſoyle be ſuffered to over-run with weedes, herbes will never roote kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and to purpoſe, therefore they that would have herbes and plants roote, doe plucke up all offenſive weedes by the rootes. And when thiſtles, nettles, and ſuch like baggage traſh are pluckt up, then good herbes and plants roote the better, and deeper. All luſts, and
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:153914:65"/> ſinnes, are ſo many weeds in our hearts, and the more theſe weeds roote in our hearts, the leſſe ſhall we root in Chriſt. But if theſe weeds be pluckt up by the rootes, and this noxious ſtuffe be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and diligently weeded out, then wee ſhall roote apace in Chriſt. Now Repentance and Mortification they weede up, and plucke up by the rootes thoſe ſinnes, and luſts, which hinder our rooting in Chriſt. So that looke what counſell the Apoſtle gives them in that caſe, is good in this. <hi>Heb. 12. 15. Looking diligently leſt any roote of bitterneſſe ſpringing up trouble you.</hi> Hee ſpeakes of Hereſies, Apoſtaſies, and Scandalls, that might fall out in the Church, every ſuch one is a roote of bitterneſſe in the Church. And ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſinne and luſt, foſtered in a mans heart, is a roote of bitterneſſe in the ſoule, and ſuch a roote of bitterneſſe, as will trouble a mans ſoule from root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Chriſt. Therefore every one that would roote in Chriſt, muſt diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly watch that no ſuch roote of bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſpring up, and grow up in his
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:153914:66"/> heart, and if any ſuch roote doe ſpring and grow up preſently, to roote it up, and roote it out. There muſt be a <hi>Root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out,</hi> if wee would have a <hi>rooting in;</hi> A rooting <hi>out</hi> of luſts, if wee would have a rooting <hi>in</hi> Chriſt. Wee know how <hi>Job</hi> ſpeakes in that caſe of the luſt of uncleaneneſſe, <hi>Job 31. 9. 12. If mine heart have been deceived by a woman, it would root out all mine increaſe.</hi> That one luſt would be enough to roote out all his ſubſtance, and all his increaſe. So it is in this caſe with any luſt, whether of uncleaneneſſe, covetouſneſſe, &amp;c. If theſe roote in the heart, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile, they will roote out all grace, and goodneſſe, and roote a man quite up for taking any roote in Chriſt. As therefore wee deſire to be rooted in Chriſt, ſo it concernes us to roote out all luſts, by repentance and mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. It is not here as in the Parable, <hi>Mat. 13. 28, 29. Wilt thou then that wee goe and gather them up? But he ſaid, Nay, leſt whileſt yee gather up the tares, yee roote up alſo the wheate with them.</hi> But here the not rooting up the tares,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:153914:68"/> will prove the hindrance of the root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the wheate. That ſoule that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers luſts to roote in it, cannot roote in Chriſt. Our luſts cannot thrive in us, and we thrive in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The conſcionable, and ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous uſe of Gods Ordinances, the Word <note place="margin">3.</note> and Sacrament. The Word is called, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1. 21. <hi>The engraffed,</hi> or <hi>Implanted Word,</hi> that is, the Word which by the Miniſtry is engraffed in our hearts. Now as it is an <hi>engraffed,</hi> ſo it is an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graffing Word, which being rightly received, doth engraff, implant, and roote us into Chriſt. The ſeede that fell upon the ſtony ground, had no Roote, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. but contrarily when the ſeede falles upon good ground it Rootes. And when the Word rootes in our hearts, it rootes us into Chriſt, for Chriſt is received in his Word. And when the Word rootes, Chriſt rootes, and when Chriſt rootes in us, wee roote in him; for it is a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and reciprocall Radication. Two things are required to make a tree or herbe roote, <hi>Planting,</hi> and <hi>watring.</hi>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:153914:69"/> The Miniſtry of the Word is both. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>Paul may plant, and Apollos may water.</hi> The Miniſtry of the Word therefore is a planting, and a watering. They therefore that would roote, muſt ſeriouſly uſe that meanes which muſt plant, and water them. And ſo for the Sacrament of the Supper, wee being once rooted by the Word, it is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent meanes to make us take deeper rooting. The barren figtree in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, <hi>Luk.</hi> 13. brought not forth fruit. There was ſome fault, not in the bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, but in the roote, and therefore the dreſſer would dig, and dung it about the roote, he would looſen and remove the hard earth from the rootes, and lay ſome mellow moulds about the roote. And wee ſee when ſuch huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry is uſed about trees, that they roote the better a great deale. The right uſe of the Sacrament, is a digging and dunging of the tree roote, is a freſh moulding of our rootes, and the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment rightly uſed, and received as it ought, will make our roote wrap about Chriſt, and ſprout, and ſpread into
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:153914:67"/> him. As therefore wee deſire to roote in Chriſt, ſo attend upon the Word and Sacrament, with that due prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and religious behaviour, as God requires. Wee ſhall finde this a ſweet fruite of theſe Ordinances duely uſed, that they will further our rooting in Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How to know whether we bee <hi>Rooted in Chriſt,</hi> or not.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>IF every true Chriſtian muſt be roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Chriſt, then as wee would know whether wee be true Chriſtians, ſo let us examine our ſelves whether wee be rooted in Chriſt or not. That may be knowne by thoſe things men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned before in the reaſons of the point. They that are rooted in Chriſt doe grow, ſuch as our growth is, ſuch is our roote: If we grow not in Chriſt, it is a ſigne wee are not rooted in him. They that are rooted beare fruit. Trees may roote, and yet not alwayes beare
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:153914:68"/> fruit. Though there can be no fruit unleſſe there be a roote, yet in naturall trees, there may be a roote where there is no fruit. But not ſo here. There is none rootes in Chriſt, but he brings forth fruite in Chriſt. The Apoſtle ſpeakes of bringing <hi>forth fruit to God, Rom.</hi> 7. 4. but he firſt ſpeakes of being <hi>married unto Chriſt,</hi> which is equivalent unto rooting. So that whoſoever is rooted in Chriſt, brings forth fruite unto God. By it may be ſeene who is not, and how many are not rooted in Chriſt. <hi>By their fruits ſhall yee know them.</hi> They bring forth no fruite unto God, therefore not rooted in Chriſt. What be the fruits they bring forth? The fruits of ſwearing, whoring, drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, prophaneneſſe, covetouſneſſe, &amp;c. Are theſe fruits unto God, or fruites unto the Devill? Doe they that are rooted in Chriſt, bring forth fruits unto Satan? Therefore in as much as the fruites that moſt men bring forth, are fruites unto the fleſh, fruites unto Satan, it is a ſigne that they are rather rooted in the fleſh, in Satan, then in
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:153914:70"/> Chriſt. And when men are ſo eaſily ſhaken and moved from the truth, it is a ſigne that they are ſtony ground, that they have no roote in themſelves. And how little men are partakers of the fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſt, appeares by the leane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and lewdneſſe of their lives. But beſides theſe, it may be diſcerned by theſe things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> By that, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 16. <hi>If the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1.</note> 
                  <hi>roote be holy, ſo are the branches;</hi> namely, the branches that are joyned to that roote. Branches then that are rooted into an holy roote, are ſuch as the root is. All that are rooted in Chriſt, are ſuch as he is. There is the ſame ſap in the roote, and branches of a tree. If a ſweet ſap in the roote, a ſweet ſap alſo in the branches. They that are rooted in Chriſt, have the ſame Spirit that is in Chriſt. <hi>Philip.</hi> 2. 5. <hi>Let the</hi> ſame minde <hi>be in you which was alſo in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Chriſt is an holy roote, all that are rooted in him are holy perſons. <hi>Jude</hi> 1. <hi>Sanctified in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> He is not onely an holy, but an hallowing Chriſt. Whatſoever touched the fleſh
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:153914:71"/> of the ſinne offering was holy. <hi>Levit.</hi> 6. 27. Whatſoever touched the Altar was holy, <hi>Exod.</hi> 30. 29. Both were types of Chriſt. Now if but the touch of Chriſt make holy, then much more when a man not touches him, but is rooted, engraffed, incorporated into him. By this may men try their Roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in Chriſt; If mens holineſſe muſt be the evidence, how many will bee cleane caſt? Let mens lives ſpeake what holineſſe they have; I doe not thinke that if men had holineſſe, they would mocke, and ſcoffe at it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> By a Radication in the grace of love and charitie. He that is <note place="margin">2.</note> rooted in Chriſt, is rooted in love. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3. 17. <hi>That Chriſt may dwell in your hearts.</hi> When Chriſt dwells in us, wee dwell in him, and when wee dwell in him, wee are rooted in him. And when thus rooted in him, ſee what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes; <hi>That yee being rooted, and ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in love;</hi> Then a man may be ſaid to be <hi>Rooted in love,</hi> when out of the ſenſe, and apprehenſion of Gods love to him in Chriſt, his love is againe kindled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:153914:69"/> God, and his neighbour, and ſo increaſes in him, that it takes daily deeper, and deeper roote in him. So then a man that rootes in Chriſt, roots in the love of God, of Chriſt, of his members. The more wee are rooted in Chriſt, the more wee are rooted in the love of God, and his Saints, and the more that love roots in our hearts. And therefore it is that faith and love doe lead hand in hand ſtill in Scripture, and that not onely love to God, but to his Saints. Let mens conſciences but ſearch themſelves, and it is to be feared that they will finde ſuch poore ſmall rootes of love to God, and his Saints, as will give them juſt cauſe to queſtion their being rooted in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> By Spirituall life, and Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition. Hee that is rooted in Chriſt, drawes life from Chriſt, and receives nouriſhment from him. A tree that is rooted in the earth, it lives by the ſap it drawes out of the earth in which it rootes. So the Chriſtian that roots in Chriſt, hee lives in Chriſt, and drawes ſap out of Chriſt, that feeds and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:153914:70"/> ſpirituall life in him. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 20. As a tree lives, yet not ſo much the tree, as the roote; and the life which the tree lives, it lives by the roote in the earth. <hi>Our life is hid with Chriſt in God,</hi> Col. 3. The life of a Chriſtian is in, and from Chriſt. Secret it is, as the life of a tree is hid in the roote which is under the earth. Doth Chriſt then quicken thee with ſpirituall life? doth he nouriſh, and feede thee with ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſap, ſo as all thou doeſt, thou doeſt by an influence of ſap, and life from him? Then conclude comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, that thou art rooted in Chriſt. But many are ſo liveleſſe, ſo dead, and ſapleſſe, that it is a ſenſeleſſe thing to conceive them other then rootleſſe Chriſtians.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:153914:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153914:73"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
